When it comes to passing a PMP exam, it
is critical to understand the PMP
mindset. In this video, I'm going to be
going over the 50 PMP mindset principles
that you need to know for your exam and
we're going to do a practice question
with each one of these principles. That
means this is about to be a really long
video because we're going to be doing 50
questions and we're going to be
explaining all of the mindset to you.
Now, these principles, where did we get
them from? Well, I created them when I
wrote the first version of my study
guide, PMP Exam Prep Simplified. I'm
Andrew Ramial, and my my book, PMP Exam
Prep Simplified, is the number one
bestselling PMP study guide in the
entire world. I'm also the creator of
UDMI's bestselling PMP course with
hundreds of thousands of students
enrolled and they're all passing their
exam. You can check the links below to
find my book and my courses. You can
also take this course on our platform.
Now,
let's just talk about this. There's a
video that a lot of you guys have been
asking me to make. There's a lot of
other videos on YouTube that talks about
the mindset. I want to point out
something. I created the PMP mindset
when I wrote the first version of my
book. In fact, most of the other
YouTubers are just repeating some of the
things that I've already taught you
guys. So, this is your going to be the
original and I'm going to call it the
Andrews official official PMP mindset.
Now, this mindset, most of it is already
taught to you if you have my 35 hour
course. By the way, my 35-hour course,
again, you can get it on UDMI or
tiaexams.com, or you can get it if you
get a copy of the book. That's free or
in the live class. All the links again
below. Now, this is going to be an
expanded version of that mindset that I
taught you in the 35 hour class as this
includes practice questions. while that
did not
uh I highly recommend that you guys do
this after your 35 hour class. Don't
watch this video until you do the 35
hour class cuz I'm on I am under the
assumptions that you did. I'm not going
to go in-depth explaining everything
because I'm assuming you already know
that. So, please watch that before doing
this video. Some of these principles
will be repeated slightly. I did that
because I wanted to either emphasize it
or just to do more practice questions on
it. So while it says 50 principles,
some of them are pretty pretty close to
to each other. Now, if you want a PDF
copy of these principles so you can
study individually or without the video
and you want to just practice the
questions, it's attached to the videos
in the courses. So make sure you get the
course. Uh if you have it on the UDI
platform, you'll see it's attached to
the lecture. It probably gave you a link
to this. Uh so you can go go to the
Udemy platform. It's going to say PMP
mindset video on YouTube. You also have
it in the TI exams platform. You can
also get the PDF there. So make sure you
get the PDF of this so you can study
these principles. And with that guys,
let's go ahead and get started uh with
these principles.
So let's get to the first principle
here.
Okay. So principle number one,
continuously identify and analyze
stakeholders, not just at the beginning
of the project. You see, throughout the
project life cycle, stakeholders come
and go. Mary is working in the
accounting department for that new
accounting application you're making.
Well, Mary got fired yesterday and she's
replaced by Jane. Now Jane is a new
stakeholder and she prefers
communications differently. A project
manager just doesn't identify and
analyze stakeholders once on a project.
They do it consistently throughout the
project as stakeholders come and go. A
couple months ago, a new regulator was
introduced to manage your type of
projects or to regulate projects that
you're currently doing. Now that's a
brand new stakeholder on a project. In
the world of traditional project
management,
the term identify stakeholders is one of
those 49 processes and is done in the
initiating part of the project. But I
want to point out that that process,
even though it's listed in initiating,
it's something that you're going to do
throughout the entire project. So keep
that in mind. Let's do a practice
question on it. Practice question number
one. Now, I want to point out before I
get into this question is that I'm just
going to be reading it and answering it.
So if you want to practice it, the best
thing you can do is pause the video. the
moment you see the question and you try
to answer it. Okay, so question number
one, you're managing a software
development project that is 60%
complete. During a sprint review, the
marketing team mentions that the new
chief marketing officer who started who
started last month has expressed
concerns about the user interface design
and wants to be involved in the upcoming
decision. What should you do first?
Couple key words in here is that we know
that we have a brand new person. notice
the new CMO and what should you do
first? A inform the marketing team that
the designs is already approved by the
stakeholders during initiation
and cannot be changed without a formal
change request. Schedule a meeting with
the new CMO to understand their concerns
and update the stakeholder to register
update the stakeholder register to
include them. Ask the marketing team to
have new the new CMO submit their
feedback through an existing project
communication channel. continue with the
current sprint as planned and address
the CMO's concern during the next
project phase. So remember the remember
principle one was to cons continuously
identify and assess these stakeholders
as the project is progressing. What
answer does that? Well, the best answer
here is going to be B. That's right.
What we want to do is we want to meet
with this new CMO. We want to understand
their concerns and we want to update
that stakeholder register. The
stakeholder register is a document that
is consistently updated throughout the
project. It's not something that's just
updated once on the project. And once
again, even though the process of
identify stakeholders is in the
initiating phase, it's something that's
done consistently throughout the
project. Anytime you have a brand new
stakeholder on a project, you must
assess what they want. And the best way
to do that is to meet with them.
generally best way face to face
understand what they're looking for,
what is their concerns, what's their
impact on the project, how does the
project impact them, and then update
your stakeholder register with that
information. And then you can make the
communication management plan and
stakeholder engagement plan to keep them
engaged. All right, let's take a look
here at principle number two.
Engage stakeholders regularly via
various channel various channels. Now I
want to point out that this is a really
important principle because you see when
you identify the previous principle is
to always identify and consistently
identify your stakeholders. We want to
keep our stakeholders engaged. I've
always told my classes this. I've told
my students this and I've told my team
members that I work with this.
The worst thing that can ever happen in
the world of managing a project is a
stakeholder that loses
interest in your project. A good project
manager will keep their stakeholders
consistently engaged on the project. How
do we do that? It might be meeting with
them. It might be giving presentation,
taking feedback, positive, negative
feedback from them, showing them a demo
of a particular product. So always
consistently engage your stakeholder on
a regular basis. Some stakeholders may
be engaged maybe once a week, maybe
daily like team members, once a week
like a sponsor, once a month like a CEO.
Different stakeholders, different
engagement, different times of
engagement, different types of
engagement. Let's take a look at a
practice question with this one.
Practice question number two. You're
managing a construction project for a
new community center with stakeholders
including city council members, local
residents, environmental groups,
contractors, and a project sponsor. You
have been sending weekly status emails
to all stakeholders for the past 3
months. But email response rates have
dropped significantly and several key
decisions are being delayed because
stakeholders not providing timely
feedback. What is the best approach to
improve stakeholder engagement? Now
before I get into this question, I want
to point out that very common on a
project, you're going to have things
like this. And if you notice these
particular things, you have many many
different kinds of stakeholders here. If
you notice, we have city council
members, right? We have uh local
residents, we have environmental groups,
we have contractors, sponsors. And what
you're doing here that's wrong is you're
basically doing one kind of
communication or engagement methods for
all of these stakeholders. And this this
is probably going to be incorrect. What
is the best approach to improve
engagements? Let's see the answers.
Increase the frequently frequency of
emails to twice a week and request read
receipts to ensure stakeholders are
receiving the information.
implement a multi- channelannel
communication approach including
face-to-face meetings, site visits,
online dashboards, and phone calls based
on stakeholder preference. Now, I think
this is a better answer so far, better
than this here because if you look at A,
A is not doing much. What A is doing is
just increasing your inefficiencies
with just those emails. You're just
making them more and you're annoying
people by having read receipts. Not the
best thing to implement. Schedule a
mandatory monthly meeting for all
stakeholders
um to discuss project status and issue
in the issue issues in person. Problem
here is going to be it's one
communication methods to all of them.
Maybe not all of them can attend the
mandatory meeting.
Create a more detailed email template
with charts and graphics to make the
status report more engaging and
informative. While this does sound good,
once again, you're basically doing one
communication methods for every
stakeholder. Remember, different
stakeholders should have different forms
of communication. Better forms of
communication
means they're going to probably be more
engaged. Let's take a look at the next
principle.
Oh, where is that? Here we go. Principle
number three. Use emotional intelligence
to assess and respond to stakeholders
needs. When issues occur with one
person, address them with that person
only. Now, I want to talk about EI.
Emotional intelligence is really, really
big on your on your exam. You see,
emotional intelligence, what this means
is understanding your emotions, how your
emotions impact how you're feeling and
how it impact others. and the ability to
read other people's emotion. So, imagine
you're engaging with a stakeholder and
you're telling them some kind of status
on the project. Can you emotionally
detect if they're really upset with you
or if they're really happy with you? Do
you understand how your persona, your
emotions is making them feel? You ever
talked to a boss before and you're like,
"Man, that guy doesn't know how to talk
to people." That's basically emotional
intelligence. emotional intelligence. If
you are a master at it, you'll be able
to master your own emotions. You'll be
able to understand how your emotions
impact others, and you'll be able to
understand other people's emotion.
Emotional intelligence is called out on
your exam objectives.
Another point here with this uh
principle
is you're going to have to deal with all
different uh stakeholders out there. And
I want to point out that a lot of times
on this exam, you can have questions
where one person is causing a problem.
Maybe this person is really loud and
makes a lot of fuss during meetings.
Maybe this person is a dominant force in
meetings. Maybe this person is
demoralizing other people, especially on
a team. Anytime mindset, anytime you
have one person doing something bad on
the project, don't confront this person
in front of everybody else. Meet with
them uh in a one-on-one setting and see
why they have this. Don't give them
solutions right away. Understand the
root cause of their problem. Why are you
like this in private? That's the main
point here. Let's go do practice
question on this one.
Practice question number three.
During a status meeting, you notice the
marketing director, who's usually very
engaged and talkative, has been
unusually quiet and appears frustrated.
When you present the timeline for the
marketing campaign launch, she briefly
responds, "Fine, whatever works."
without her typical detailed questions
or suggestions. What should you do next?
Now, I want to point out that this is
this is going to be with that principle
three mindset and notice this is a
problem with just this particular
person. So, what should we do? All
right, let's see here. Continue with
your plan work since you said the
timeline was acceptable. Put on my pen
here. And you have and you have urgent
deliverables to complete. probably not
the best answer here because what you're
doing is you're just doing nothing. Part
of the mindset is never do nothing. In
this one, you're not really helping this
person. You know they're upset. You
notice they appear upset, unusually
quiet. So, you're detecting this is good
emotional intelligence. You detect that
whenever they say fine, whatever works,
your emotional intelligence, your EI is
telling you this person is really upset.
Just don't leave the stakeholders like
that, especially since they're a
director and they're probably a senior
stakeholder. So, I wouldn't do it.
Send a follow-up email to all attendees
asking if there are any concerns about
the timeline that weren't addressed. Not
a good answer here. Also, here's why.
You're sending a follow-up email to all
attendees. You know, the problem is with
one of the attendees, not all of them.
So, let's address it with that person,
not all. This the question doesn't say
everybody else was upset. Reach out
privately to the marketing director to
check if everything is okay. I
understand if there are any other there
any uh underlying concerns. I like this
answer. So I'm going to leave this one.
I'm not going to put X on it. D.
Schedule another meeting with all
stakeholders to revisit the timeline
discussions and ensure everyone is truly
aligned. The only person that's not
truly aligned here is the marketing
director. So I think we need to keep our
discussions with that marketing
director. In this question, we used our
emotional intelligence to detect, hey,
this person was not happy with what's
going on on the project. And then we
reached out. We used that principle of,
hey, you know what? Let's go ahead and
just engage that single person in there.
All right, let's take a look here, guys,
at principle number four.
Document all impacted individuals as
stakeholders. Even if their involvement
is indirect. If someone is impacted
positively or negatively, they're a
stakeholder. One of the things we have
to understand is who are stakeholders on
a project. On a project, anyone and I
mean anyone or groups of people that are
positively and or negatively impacted
our stakeholders. We want to document
them in our stakeholder register and we
want to analyze them. We want to tailor
our communications to them. We want to
tailor, for example, progress reports or
um project reports to them. Now, I
really put this principle here because I
want you guys to understand that when
people are positively impacted, they're
a stakeholder and negatively. A lot of
people think that if you're positively
impacted, for example, you're working in
a company and there's a new AI software
coming out and it's going to help make
your work a lot easier. Most people
think those are stakeholders. What
people forget is that Bob who is losing
his job because of your new AI software.
Bob is also a stakeholder. So keep in
mind not just people that are positively
impacted or stakeholder. It's people
that are negatively impacted. Let's say
they're building a highway next to your
house.
Well, you're not happy about that. The
noise, the pollution,
but you know what? you're going to be
negatively impacted, but you're also
going to be positively impacted because
now you can use the highway to get to
work 10 minutes earlier. So, always
remember positive and negatively
impacted are cons folks that are
positively negatively impacted are
considered stakeholders. Let's take a
look at take a look at a question on
this.
Question four. You're managing a project
to implement a new CRM, customer
relation management system for the sales
department. During a requirement
gathering session, you learned that the
new CRM will automatically generate
reports that the finance team uses for
commission calculations and will
integrate with the customer service
system that tracks warranty claims. What
should you do regarding the finance and
customer service teams? A keep them off
the stakeholder register since they
wouldn't directly use the CRM system but
ensure the integration requirements are
documented in scope. I wouldn't do this
because remember what the principle says
positively and or negatively impacted
directly and indirectly impacted those
are all stakeholders. So let's not do
this.
Add both team to the stakeholder
register and include them in the project
communications even though their
involvement is indirect. I think this is
a decent answer because we're adding
them to the stakeholder register which
means we're going to be analyzing their
needs. We're going to be communicating
with them. We're going to probably be
giving them updates.
Contact the finance and customer service
team only if the integration issues
arise during the implementation to avoid
unnecessary project complexity. No, I
would put them in the stakeholder
register. Ask the sales director to
coordinate with finance and customer
service teams on your behalf since they
understand the business relationship
better. So I wouldn't do this. All
right? Uh I wouldn't give away the work.
Part of the mindset is never to give
away your work like that. So, I think
the best answer here, guys, is going to
be B. Add them to that stakeholder
register
because even though they're somewhat
indirectly impacted while it's going on,
they're going to be directly impacted
when the project is finished and they're
using the applications. So, remember
indirect or directly impacted, they're a
stakeholder. Positive, negatively
impacted, they're still a stakeholder.
All right, let's take a look here, guys,
at the next principle. Principle five.
Principle number five, don't dismiss
customer requests prematurely. Evaluate
each one carefully.
Don't do nothing when someone has asked
for for any for anything. I added this
here right before this video. I always
tell my students this. If you get a
question where a stakeholder has some
kind of a problem or they have some kind
of issue with something or they're
asking some kind of question and the
there's a choice to like not do anything
or not help this person or ignore this
person, it's never the answer. A good
project manager is proactively engaging,
speaking and communicating with the
stakeholders on a cons consistent basis.
So keep that in mind. Don't push people
off. So, in this one, never dismiss a
customer request. Anytime a customer
asks something, at least tell them
something. Assess something for them.
Give them feedback on what they're
asking. And never do nothing. If there's
a choice, uh, one of the four choices
that says, uh, let it be and you'll talk
about it later, it's probably not the
answer. Let's take a look at a practice
question on this principle.
question.
You're managing a website redesign
project that is 75% complete and on
track to finish on time and within
budget. That's good. The client calls
you with a request to add a new chatbot
feature that they saw on a competitor's
website, which would require significant
additional work and potentially delayed
a project by three to four weeks. What
should you do first?
All right. So they want to add something
that's going to significantly increase
the schedule. What are we doing first
here? Meet with the client to understand
the business value and urgency of the
chatbot feature. Then analyze the impact
across all the knowledge area scope,
schedule, quality before making any
decisions. I like that answer. It's not
bad. Why? Because you're addressing the
customer concerns. You're not just
pushing it away. Inform the client that
adding a new feature at this stage would
cause significant delays and cost
overruns and suggest they consider it
for a future phase. Well, I don't like
this answer. You know why? Because
you're just dismissing the client.
You're not really understanding
why this client wants this. You know, I
want to point out something.
We do projects not for us. We do
projects for our clients. We do it for
our customers. When the customer wants
something, just don't dismiss them and
say, "Hey, we're not going to do that
for you." Remember, we're not doing
these for us. We're doing it for them.
Ask the development team to provide a
detailed estimate for the chatbot
feature so you can present the client
with accurate cost and schedule impacts.
Oo, that's a good one, too. So, A and C,
decent answers, right? Because we didn't
dismiss them, but we tell them we're
going to assess it for them.
D. Explain to the client that the scope
is already approved and any changes
would require going through a formal
change control procedure. Oh, this is a
good one. So, we're we're telling them,
hey, if you want this, fill out this
change request.
Uh, A is meet with the client to
understand the business value.
Uh, D is tell them, hey, follow this
particular change.
What answer would you go with? Okay, the
key word to get this one correct is
going to be notice it says first. That
arrow should be pointed first by the way
is a before you tell this person, hey,
go fill out a change request or before
you have the team go ahead and um before
you have the team assess the feature to
really see how much it's going to
increase the scope and the time and cost
and all that. Before you do all of that,
why don't you meet with this person
first? Why don't you understand the
business value? So that way you and your
team can then have a good understanding
of exactly what they want. So before you
have this person um
go through the formal change control
process, before you have your team do
anything, let's meet with the client and
let's go ahead and
understand what they want.
All right, let's take a look here at the
next principle. Now, these principles
here are going to be change management.
Let's cut off a little there. We got six
principles on change management.
All right, principles number six. Now,
we're talking about changes.
All right, change changes is important.
Uh on a project, you are going to be
asked to change things.
They're going to ask you, you're
managing a project, somebody's going to
come to you, can you add this to the
scope? Can you remove this to the scope?
Can you make it cheaper? Can you make it
faster? These are common changes that
you should expect. The question is, how
are you going to manage these particular
changes? That's the main that's the main
key here.
And the way we manage changes is going
to be different depending on whether
you're doing that agile project or that
traditional project. Let's see. Let's
see what this principle is about.
Traditional. So if you're managing a
traditional project, you want to follow
the plan. Do not allow changes without
an approved change request. Whenever you
can, always follow the plan. Now what do
I mean by that? On a traditional
project, you have this giant hopefully
you studied your you watch your 35 hour
class with me. You remember me talk a
lot about this giant project management
plan. It has all these components, all
those 18 plans and the baselines and
everything like that. Your objective
when that project execute is to follow
the plan. If it's not in the plan, don't
do it. If somebody wants to add
something to the scope, they first need
to go through an entire change control
process and get it approved by maybe the
sponsor or the change control board. So
if it's not in the plan, you don't do
it. You must have them submit it as a
change request and then add it to the
plan.
Now any changes to the PM plan must
follow a detailed change management
process and never implement a change
without assessing it. One of the common
questions you get on your exam is
somebody wants a change or one of the
choices is going to say implement the
change to keep the pro project on track.
It's never the answer on a traditional
project. Never implement the change
without assessing it. Now this of course
will change drastically. The whole
change management process will change
drastically when we come to agile
project management.
Just a quick review in agile project
management the scope itself is managed
in the product backlog. In traditional
project the scope is on the scope
baseline. So here we have the uh on on
the agile project here we have um the
product backlog which is man managed by
the product owner. On an agile project,
change is welcome and managed through
backlog prioritization and sprint
planning rather than formal change
control processes. Only the product
owner can add to the product backlog.
What do we mean by that? Well, on an
agile project when somebody wants a
change, when somebody wants to add
something, for example, to the scope,
basically it's told to the product owner
and the product owner really decides if
we should add it to the product backlog,
which is like their scope statement. And
then the product owner determines how to
prioritize it. Does it go to the top of
the backlog? Does it go to the bottom,
middle, and so on? This is outside the
control of the project manager. So keep
that in mind. Traditional, somebody
wants a change to something, they got to
follow the change control process. We
have to assess it before we approve it.
In agile, they want a change. They talk
to the product owner. The product owner
decides whether to add it into the
product backlog or not. So, keep that in
mind. When somebody wants a change on a
project, let's do a question on this.
Question number six. A project manager
is leading an agile software development
project when the product owner requests
to add a new feature that would enhance
user security. The feature was not in
the original requirements and would
require significant development effort.
The team is currently in a middle of a
twoe sprint with committed deliverables.
What should the project manager do? So I
want to point out that this is a
practice question that deals with agile
projects. You got to remember the agile
project principle.
What should the project manager do?
Submit the new feature through a formal
change control process for approval.
Probably not. Why? Because remember what
I said. This is an agile project and
they don't have a formal change control
system. Work with the product owner to
add the security feature to the product
backlog for prioritization. I like that.
Okay. Remember, you're not adding it.
The only person that can add something
to the product backlog is a product
owner, not the project manager, not the
project team. immediately
incorporate the feature into the current
sprint to address security concerns
wrong. You can't just add something in.
At no point is a project manager allowed
to add to the scope. Traditional and or
agile. Keep that in mind, okay? Because
in a traditional project, it has to go
through a formal change control process
which is generally going to be approved
by the sponsor. In an agile project,
it's a product owner. At no point should
the project manager be adding anything
to the scope statement and or the
product backlog.
Reject the request since it wasn't part
of the original project scope. I want to
point this out again. You never ever
reject a change on a project. It's not
your authority to reject changes.
Anybody that wants to change goes
through the change control process and
or they will go through the product
owner. So keep in mind that the best
answer here is of course going to be B.
Let's work with the product owner.
Somebody wants to add a feature. Work
with the product owner to get that done.
Now I do expect quite a few questions on
this particular topic because on this
topic changes is something that all
project managers will deal with. Let's
take a look at the next principle.
Principle number seven.
Any stakeholder requesting changes to
the project management plan must submit
a change request. This is common. If you
are on a traditional project and
somebody comes to you and says, "Hey,
Andrew, I want to um
add some work to your scope. The best
thing you can do is well, if you really
want this, you know, meet with them,
understand why they want this, but for
it to go through, they got to submit a
formal change request. This is going to
be a document where they document the
change so you can assess it.
Agile is going to be different. Agile
handle changes through direct
collaboration with the product owner who
prioritize a request in a product
backlog without a formal change request.
So this is very very similarly related
to the other principle is that hey when
somebody wants to change make sure to
submit a change request and in agile
there's really nothing there with change
requests. They just give it to the
product owner. Let's take a look at a
question on this.
Question seven.
During your weekly status meeting, the
sponsor mentions that due to new
regulatory requirements, the project
timeline needs to be accelerated by one
month to meet a compliance deadline. The
sponsor states, "This is critical for
the business and needs to happen.
What should you do next?" Now, I want to
point out that this, you can see right
off the bat, is a traditional project.
And you're asking, how does he know
that? Well, notice it doesn't really say
product owner. It says product sponsor,
right? Project sponsor. So, this it's
not a this is more than likely not a
agile project. So, we're going to follow
those traditional rules.
What you do next? Begin working with a
team immediately to develop a compressed
schedule that meets the sponsor's
requirement. See, this is probably not
right. Now, the reason for that is
because notice you implemented the
change right away. Ask sponsor submit a
form of change request detail and
regulatory requirements and timeline
changes before proceeding. Okay. Analyze
the current schedule to identify
opportunities for compression and
present options for the sponsor. Here
you're you're doing something without
getting the formal change request.
Schedule a follow-up meeting and key
take discuss the impact of the
accelerated timeline. Let them submit
it. let's analyze it before we doing
this. The next thing you should do is
hey sponsor calls you up and says hey
can you get this done and you're like
your next response should be okay let's
get that change request let's detail
exactly what you're looking for making
be the best answer on this one and
that's something that you want to
consistently point out that I should
point out on a consistent basis is that
you have to always assess changes before
implementing them on a traditional
project. I know I said that 500 times,
but it's important. Let's take a look at
the next principle, guys. Principle
number eight.
Now, principle number eight here is a
traditional thing. All changes must be
reviewed and assessed. I want to point
that out in particular.
You know, this something we just talked
about.
Anytime somebody submit a change, and
more than likely for your exam, it's
going to be a scope change. As we see
here, you want to assess it. A scope
change must be assessed across all the
other knowledge areas. And that's going
to be when somebody changes scope,
assess to see how that affects time or
schedule, budget, quality requirements,
people requirements, right? How many
more people or physical materials you
need, communication requirements? Is
that going to change? How much risk does
it add or remove? Does it do you need
new contractors? Does it change the way
stakeholders are engaging? So keep that
in mind that anytime a scope somebody
wants to change a scope, more than
likely it's going to affect almost all
aspects of the project and you really
need to assess that. Let's do a question
on this.
Question number eight.
You receive a change request from the
marketing team to add a social media
integration feature to your mobile app
project. The request seems
straightforward and your lead developer
mentions it would be easy to add an
estimates about two days of work. Okay,
not too bad, right? Somebody's asking to
add something in. This is definitely a
scope change.
Two days of work. What should you do? A
approve the change immediately since
it's low risk and a team has done
similar work. Well, first of all, the
project manager doesn't have the
authority to just approve work. So, I'm
going to eliminate it. Ask the marketing
team to wait until the next change
control board meeting to maintain proper
governance. Never ask people to wait.
That's part of the mindset. Don't tell
people to wait or push things off. So,
let's not go with this one at all here.
Conduct a thorough assessment of the
change change request on scope,
schedule, cost, quality, and risk before
making any decisions. Okay, that's
that's good. So notice that you're
assessing this change against lots of
different aspects of the project. I like
that. Since it's urgent and seems
simple, implement the feature now and
document the changes. No, you'll notice
that D,
which is just implement the change right
away. And A, approve the change yourself
basically is basically the same answer.
Best answer here guys is just like the
the the mindset is telling us make sure
we assess how these changes affects the
entire project. And this is a question
that you're going to see a lot of. All
right. A lot of people would ask
questions. You're probably going to get
three or four questions on the exam that
talks about asking for changes.
Remember, don't approve of a change
until you've assessed that change.
All right, let's go ahead and take a
look here at the next series of
principles. We got quite a few
principles 9 to 17 deals with decision-
making and problem solving. Now, I want
to point out that your exam,
more than half of it is going to be
dealing with problems. I wouldn't be
surprised 180 questions, 90 to 100
questions is some kind of problem.
Problem with a vendor, problem with a
customer, problem with a team member,
problem with regulators, problem with
senior management, problem with
equipment. Your your your exam has a lot
of things that deals with problems. So
how are we going to deal with this?
Let's take a look at these principles.
Now principle number nine.
Now traditional
how do we deal with problems? First of
all never act without a plan. Planning
is done once for the entire project.
This is important.
Anytime a problem arise
and problems are more than likely are
issues, right? So what's an issue? An
issue is something that has occurred
that is negative on your project that
has to be fixed.
The reason why we have plans in place,
the reason why you have that giant
project management plan in place is that
when an issue arise, a problem, some
something happens on a project, the plan
tells you how to fix it. For example,
let's say you're working on a project
and there's a problem that's going to
delay the project. Well, how do you deal
with schedule issues? Well, read the
schedule management plan. That's why you
have it in the first place. There's a
problem with uh Mary having an issue
with Jane.
Well, read your resource management
plan. That tells you how to manage and
manage conflicts on a project because
the resource management plan tells you
how to manage resources. Those
management plans are there to tell you
how to manage your project. So before
you actually take an action against
something, review your plans and see if
the plans will tell you how to fix your
problem. So never act without a plan.
See if there's a plan in place for it.
Again, that's why in tradition you have
this giant plan. I want to point out
that in a tradition of project planning
is done once. So you make this giant
project management plan. You execute the
whole project and hopefully you never
need to change it.
Agile is a little different. Agile
embraces iterative planning where plans
are created just in time for each
sprint. So remember in agile they do
sprint after sprint after sprint. Each
sprint does a certain amount of work.
What they do is they plan right before
the sprint for just that amount of work.
This is done during the sprint planning
meeting. Don't forget you can replace
the word sprint with word iteration. So
it's basically you know people say isn't
a tradition isn't an agile project like
a traditional project where chop up the
work somewhat yes but not really but I
do want to point out that in agile we do
have we do do planning for the work that
we're about to do in the sprint planned
meeting all right let's see a practice
question on this
question nine your data migration
project is scheduled to begin the
database transfer this weekend when you
discover on Friday afternoon that the
backup verification process failed and
the backup files are corrupted. Oh, that
sounds bad guys. The project has already
announced the system downtime to users
vendors has been scheduled and the
migration team is standing by. What
should you do? Okay, so the backup
failed. We got a problem here. uh they
announce it to the the to the users.
What do you mean? So this is obviously
the problem. What should you do? Hey,
immediately start working on alternative
backup solutions as directed while the
IT director develops the evolve
strategy. All right. Postpone the
migration until a complete backup
recovery plan can be developed and
tested. All right. Call emergency
planning session to develop
comprehensive approach for addressing
backup issues before taking any
corrective actions. Okay, I like this. I
like this. This is not a bad answer
immediately. I wouldn't do a You know
why? Because a you're working here
without a plan. You just start doing
things. I don't want to postpone until
all until a complete backup. I think
before we do this, I think we may want
to, you know, have a good plan in place
to fix it. Begin the migration of
schedule, but implement additional
monitor. I think we should come up with
a plan first and address this. This is a
major issue. All right. Not having
backup files. Something is overwritten.
and you'll never get the data back. So I
think the best answer here guys is going
to be C, which is you know what, let's
create a plan. Remember, don't act
without a plan. Let's have that plan in
place before we move forward.
And now on your exam, they're probably
going to mention something, but
management plans. Always make sure you
follow those management plans because
that's what they're there for. All
right, let's go in here to principle 10.
Principle 10, consult the team before
making decisions. They often have
practical insights and expertise. Don't
act alone. So this is both traditional
and agile. The best people to make the
decisions on a project is your team. The
best people to give you estimates, the
best people to solve problems, to solve
issues are the experts. And by
definition, the team is your experts. So
let's work with the team on getting this
done. So, always remember if there's a
problem on a project, try to meet with
your team to solve those problems. Let's
take a look at a practice question on
this
question.
Question 10. You're managing a software
development project and need to choose
between two technical architecture
approaches for the new system. As the
PM, you have researched boat options
thoroughly and have a clear preference
based on your analysis of cost,
timeline, and alignment with business
requirements. What should you do? Make
the architectural decision based on your
research. Present it to the sponsor,
then inform the team of decision
afterwards to avoid disrupting their
current work. Well, this one goes
against the principal, doesn't it? The
principal says, "Let's work with the
team here." This one here is just you
doing it on your exam. Don't do things
by yourself. Just don't make decisions.
The project manager is there to
facilitate everyone so decisions are
made, not just to make all the decisions
by yourself.
Present both options to the sponsor with
your recommendation and let them make
the final decisions since they have
business authority. Although I do agree
that sponsors does have the final
authority, I do want to point out that
hey, you know what? um we don't want
them we we don't want to just push it
upon them and because we did the
analysis we feel it's best. I think
we're missing the experts here.
Delay the decision until the development
teams complete the current sprint and
can give the architectural choice their
full attention.
Okay, not too bad. I don't like this
delay thing, but it does involve the
team. Consult with the development team
about both ar about both architect
options before making your final
recommendation. I think this is going to
be our best answer. We don't want to
delay anything. Now I want to point out
that the question did state two
technical architectural approaches. A PM
is not going to be the subject matter
expert on everything that we do. So as
the PM you have to research both
options. making D here the best answer
because remember it is technical and
even though you did the research let's
get the team involvement to give us a
much much better understanding of this.
We just finished 10 of those principles
and 10 practice questions. If you're
enjoying this video, did you give the
video a like? Did you subscribe to the
channel? It helps us out immensely. If
you guys don't like the videos and you
don't subscribe to the channel, we don't
make more content like this as we don't
know how relevant it is. So, just takes
a second, just a little tap. I know we
got to beg, but we got to feed the
algorithm its uh its food this morning.
Let's go back to the principles.
Okay, next principle. Principle 11.
Choose actions that best serve project
objective and deliver the highest value
to the stakeholders. I mentioned this
earlier. We do projects for
stakeholders. We don't do projects for
us. We don't do projects for the team
member. The by definition the customers
are the ones that will gain the benefits
of the project. So we should do what's
right for them. Couple scenarios of this
would be when the team
uh the customer wants a feature but the
team is like that feature is too hard.
We don't want to do that. That's
probably not right. All right. The
customer is who we're doing this for. Do
it for what's best for the customer. Do
it what's best for the overall project.
Right? So then you're going to at that
moment the team has got to take a
backseat. We got to get it done because
the customer is the most important one.
If something is going to if you have to
make a decision on this exam that
satisfy Jane or satisfies the project
objectives Jane being a team member
satisifi satisfy your project objectives
first. Let's do a practice question on
this one.
Question 11. your e-commerce platform
project that has three critical issues
that needs immediate attention, but you
have but you only have resources to
address one this week. A security
vulnerability that could potentially
expose customer data. Okay. A
performance issue uh causing slow
checkout times that are reducing sales.
All right. And a cosmetic bug that the
CEO noticed and specifically acts to be
fixed. The development team is waiting
for your prioritized decision. Now, in
this question, they're specifically
asking you to choose it. So, what do you
choose? Well,
you only have resources to do one this
week. What are we doing? Well, hey, fix
the security to prevent potential data
breaches and protect customer
information even though it hasn't been
exploited yet. I like this one. I'm a
security guy. I like that answer. You
know why? Because in the long run for
the overall objectives if there is a
massive security flaw customer data is
lost. This can of course have a drastic
negative impact on the project and the
business
resolve the performance issue. Now since
it's actively impacting customer
experience and business revenue right
now although this is bad this is more
shortterm right even though they're
going to lose a little bit of money now
they're not going to lose their whole
business. So I would do A before I do B.
Address the cosmetic bug first is the
CEO. Now, even though the CEO is a
senior stakeholder, we're not denying
it. We'll probably fix it later. But in
this one here, this is just a cosmetic
bug and it's not going to affect the
entire project.
Split the team's time. This is not an
option because it's literally telling
you you can only do one. So, don't go
against the question. If a question says
you you only have one guy to do one
task, then just do one task. Don't don't
tell a guy to work three tasks. So the
best answer here guys is to do what's
right for the entire project. Not just
what's right for salespeople or what's
right for the CEO. This particular thing
was right for the entire project. So
always try to satisfy what's right for
your entire project.
Next principle principle 12.
Understand the root of conflict before
resolving it. Don't attempt to resolve a
conflict without understanding the main
cause. In the Penach guide, and this is
by the way both agile and traditional in
the Penach guide, one of they have this
conflict management series of steps. And
the first thing is to understand the
conflict. You could never totally
solve conflicts or problems unless you
really understand what is the main cause
of the problem.
For example, let's say you have Bob and
Mary having an issue and Bob says we
should put this uh application in the
cloud. Mary says we should keep it on
site and they're going back and forth
and back and forth and you you listen to
the issue. The main thing you should
understand is why do you guys want why
are we fighting over cloud versus
onsite? What is the root cause of this?
And after Jordan, you came to understand
that they are fighting over performance
problems. So then the the way to
actually fix this problem is to choose
the answer that best resolves the
performance issues. Things like this we
have to keep in mind. Never solve a
problem until you actually understand
it. On this exam you're going to get
questions where they're going to say
what should you do next? And the thing
you should do next when it comes to
problems is to understand what's causing
that problem. Let's take a look at a
question on this.
Question 12.
During your weekly team meeting, a
heated argument breaks out between the
lead developer and the QA manager about
testing timelines. The developer insists
that QA is being unreasonable by
demanding too much time for testing,
while the QA manager argues that the
developer is rushing the code and
creating quality problems. By the way,
this seems like a really
common thing. What should you do first?
Stop the argument immediately and remind
both members about professional behavior
and expect expectations and meet it.
One of the things we want to do is not
to be mean. Part of the mindset, don't
be mean. Don't come off as a tyrant.
Hey, you guys need to stop and be
professional. Probably not the best
answer. Schedule a separate one-on-one
meetings with each team member to
understand their underlying concern and
perspective before attempting
resolution. Okay, it's not bad. All
right, just trying to get to the cause.
Implement a new process that allocates
specific time for development and
testing to prevent future. This is no
good.
In this one, you are not really coming
to understand the problem. You're just
going out on fixing the problem. D.
Facilitate a discussion between both
team members to find a compromise on the
testing timeline that works for
everyone. Now, this is a good answer.
You got two choices.
You got B, where your one-on-one
meetings with each member, and you got
D, you're scheduling discussion between
the members to find a compromise on the
test and timeline. I like both answers.
But remember, before we solve the
problem, we really have to understand
what's going to what's the main cause.
What's the underlying cause here of
these problems before attempting some
kind of resolution? Uh I would do B then
I would do D. All right? So let's do B.
Let's meet oneonone and then let's do D.
Now we understand now we can better
facilitate. It's hard to facilitate a
discussion between people if you really
don't understand what the problem is. So
let's do B then let's do D. Always
remember for your exam never ever
solve problems without understanding the
root cause of those problem.
Next principle. Principle 13. When an
issue happens, enter it into the issue
log. Check the risk register for
responses to issues. Now, what exactly
is an issue versus a risk? Let's break
this down first in this principle. A
risk is something that's positive or
negative that has not happened yet. It
has a probability. It it is uncertain if
this event will take place. For example,
having bad weather during the winter,
that's a risk. But if you are in a storm
right now and it's a blizzard, well,
that's considered an issue. An issue is
something that has happened and is
generally negative that's affecting your
project. Risk, we'll talk about later on
a few more principles down. In this one,
I want to concentrate on issues. So,
when an issue occurs, I want you right
away to put it in the issue log. We have
an issue log for a reason. The moment it
happens, put it in the issue log. One
thing that confuses students is when I
say, "Well, where, you know, where do we
find a resolution to the to the issue?
Where do we come up with how to solve
it?" Check the risk register. That
sounds kind of weird, right? The risk
register has a resolution to the issues.
Yeah. Here's why. Because before it was
an issue, you should have anticipated
this issue and documented as a risk.
For example, let's say you're going to
build a house during the winter. You
know that during the winter there are
blizzards that can delay the project. So
what you do is you put in your risk
register blizzards and you put well stop
the project on till the snow is cleared.
That's your response. Now you're
building the house and it's January and
there's a blizzard that just happened.
What you do is you take out the word
blizzard, you copy it from the risk
register and you put it into the issue
log. The response to the blizzard you
already thought about, right? The
response to this issue that's happening
right now, you already thought about
it's to delay a project by a few days.
So what do you do? You take the response
from the risk register and you put it
next to the issue or you start enacting
that potent potential response. So I
want you guys to remember that before
you come up with resolution to issues,
you if one of the choices is like check
the risk register for the responses,
it's probably going to be the answer.
Let's do a practice question on this.
Question 13. During a new software
project, a team member newly written
code is crashing a few modules that was
written a few weeks ago. This will cause
this will cause a major delay if not
fixed right away and the team member is
uncertain of how to fix it. What should
the project manager do first? Add this
code to the issue log and assign an
owner. Okay, I like that. It's it is an
issue. add this risk to the risk
register and work with the team to fix
it. No, this is not a risk because you
notice is crashing a few module that
means that this is happening right now.
It's not something that's uncertain or
something that's potential that would be
a risk. Assign a senior coder to fix it.
Well, you shouldn't just come up with a
resolution just like that. Let's put it
in issue lock first. Discuss a
facilitation disc facilitate a
discussion between team members to fix a
code in error. I like D. D is not a bad
answer, but you know what it wants to
what do you do first? Let's do A first
and then we'll do D. Make an A the best
answer on this particular one. So I want
you guys to remember anytime there is an
issue, make sure you put it in that
issue log first. Check that risk
register. If that's not an answer,
right? If adding it to the issue log is
not an answer, if A wasn't there, I
would have probably then gone with D
because that would have been the first
thing to do is discuss it with the team
members. But if that's an answer, make
sure you select that one first.
Next principle when confused, refer to
subject matter experts, lesson learned
register from past projects or your
organizational process assets. I want to
point out uh something here. Project
managers are not subject matter experts.
All right? That's not who we are. We're
not subject matter experts. We are good
facilitators. A good project manager is
not an expert programmer. The greatest
project managers have great people
skills and they can facilitate well. Not
somebody that is a massive programmer or
somebody that is a
super construction engineer or
something. I'm not saying those people
can't be good project managers but
people's skill is more value. Lesson
learned register from from past projects
is of course going to be important.
Lesson learn registers is what this is
something that we document throughout
the project. As the project is
progressing we are documenting
all of the lesson learned throughout the
project and then we give it to all the
project managers when the project is
done throughout the project. So one of
the best ways to learn from or to fix
things is just to look back on previous
lessons.
Sometimes organizations may have
templates or knowledge bases that we can
look at. Those would all be considered
an OPA. Many organizations have
encountered some types of problems like
regulatory fixes and so on. So this is a
good place to look. The point of this
one here is that we are not subject
matter experts and we should always look
for help. Let's let's do a question on
this.
Question 14. You're managing your first
healthcare IT project involving HIPPO
compliance
requirements when a complex technical
issue emerges regarding data encryption
standards. You've researched online and
found conflicting information about the
specific requirements and your team is
waiting for guidance with a decision
needed by tomorrow. What should you do?
Make the decision.
Make the make the best decision you can
based on your research and move forward.
Adjust and later if needed to show
decisive leadership. No, I don't want
you to make this decision. It says your
first IT project involving HIPPA. So
you've probably never done this.
Probably not your best decision.
Escalate decision to your sponsor since
complex compliance issues are above your
authority. Your sponsor is probably not
a subject matter expert on this. Let's
not go over this. Call a team brainstorm
to collectively research encryption and
reach a consensus. Although I like this
answer. Let's put on back burner. Let's
see what he says. It's not a bad answer.
Consult with the company's HIPPA
compliance officer. This is better.
Review lesson learns for previous
healthcare and check the organizational
uh compliance procedures. This is
definitely a better answer because this
indeed we know we're meeting with the
subject matter expert versus a we're not
sure if the team is always seek out the
advice of the subject matter expert
before moving forward on a project.
Never assume you are. That's the point
of that principle. Let's take a look at
the next principle 15. Always
investigate and consult before acting
especially when the questions asks what
the PM should do first or next any you
should never fix things first you should
never act first review your plan meet
with people talk to people before doing
something first in real life you do this
when something happens you review your
plans in your head and review your
documents before you actually go out and
fix things you're just doing randomly
just go start doing random actions
Right? You think about the actions
before you do them.
Never choose to fix an issue without
analyzing that issue first. This
something we said, make sure to analyze
that issue. Let's see a practice
question on this. This going to be a
really common one on your on your exam.
Question 15. You arrive at work to find
an urgent voicemail
from a key client stating that they're
extremely disappointed with the latest
deliverable and are considered
terminating the contract. The client
demands an immediate response and the
team is asking what's happening as word
has spread quickly. What should you do
first? So now I like this question
because this question is like forcing
you to do it right away, right? It's
like hey do this right now. What should
you do first? Call the client
immediately to apologize for the dis
disappointment and assure them that
you'll personally resolve whatever the
issues they have. In real life, that
might be a decent answer, but personally
resolved, I don't like that answer.
Review the deliverable that was
submitted. Check the acceptance
criteria. Gather information about what
specifically disappointed the client
before pro responded. I like this one
here. You're checking, you're reviewing,
you're analyzing. I like this schedule
emergency meeting with your sponsor
because how to respond to the clients.
One of the part of the mindset you'll
learn later is never give away your
work. Just don't go to the sponsor.
Contact your sponsor to inform them of
the client's threat and get guidance on
how to proceed. Yeah. Don't ask for help
on a project. You should never just go
out and ask, especially when something
is within your jurisdiction to fix.
Ask for help. Okay, I want to point this
out clearly. Ask for help on subject
matter stuff
like programming, HIPPA compliance.
Don't ask for help on project management
stuff like managing your stakeholders.
That's project management stuff. That's
project management task. But when it
comes to like if there's a problem with
a regulation,
there's a problem with a uh coding
error, there's a problem with a
building, something like that, go get
the right subject matter expert. But in
the world of project management here,
you're dealing with a stakeholder. This
is your jurisdiction. You got to fix
this. So what exactly is the best
answer? Well, the best answer here is
going to be to review it. Don't take an
action against it. Let's review it
first. And that's going to be a theme of
this exam because this principle is
going to apply to many many of those
questions.
Next principle,
show progress through tangible outputs
such as minimum viable products, MVPs or
prototypes.
As you're progressing through the
project and you're making decisions,
right? Customer says they like this,
they don't like this. The best thing we
can do is give them something to use.
Customers have a weird way of saying
what they want. When you give them what
they want, it's not what they really
want. You see, what's in my head for me
to explain what I wanted, what I want,
and I tell it to you, there's a little
bit that's lost between my explanation
to you and how you understand it. The
best way to really see if you designed
or built what I wanted is to actually
give me something that's usable,
tangible, that I can physically use it
and actually gain benefit from it. And
that's an MVP, right? So an MVP, a
minimum viable product is something that
we can release into production that you
guys can start using and gaining value
from. Prototypes are things that you may
not be able to use, but you'll be able
to experience it. You're not going to
gain much value in terms of making money
from it.
um it's more like a demo product versus
an MVP you can use in production and do
your work with. So a prototype is
something that you may be able to touch
and feel and give good feedback on. In
both of these scenarios, you're actually
the customer is actually having hands-on
with whatever is it that you're making.
Let's do a question on this
number 16. Question 16. The mobile app
development project is now 50% complete
according to the schedule, but
stakeholders are expressing concerns
about the project's progress and
questioning whether the final product
will meet their expectation. The
development team has been following
agile practices but hasn't yet delivered
any work and functionality that
stakeholders can see or test.
What should you do to address the
stakeholders concern? So, let's redo
this.
They're expressing concern, right? So,
what is the main concern? They're
concerned about the progress whether it
will meet their expectations. Well, they
haven't seen it yet.
Um, you have been following agile but
haven't delivered any work in
functionality. Maybe this is the
problem. All right. What should you do
to address these concerns?
Create a detailed status report showing
percentage completion for each features
and present them to the stakeholders.
Completion report. You telling
stakeholders things are done doesn't
really give them much other than verbal
com verbal or written confirmation that
something is done.
Organize a demonstration session where
the development team can show
stakeholders the working components and
core core functionality. I like that.
Now we can actually show them what we're
doing. Schedule a weekly meeting to
provide verbal updates on development
progress and address their concerns. I
don't like this answer. In fact, I think
A is probably better than C in this
scenario. In this one, once again,
you're just telling them it's updated
versus showing them. Reassure
stakeholders a project is on track
according to the schedule and ask them
just to ask them to trust it. The best
thing here we can do is to meet with the
stakeholders to show them what was done.
I want to point out that on your exam,
you will get questions that will deal
with the answer being minimum viable
products. It's one of the hot topics on
your test. It's in the exam objectives.
Make sure you really understand it. It's
one of the best ways for customers to
give you feedback and to get early value
from the products we're delivering on
agile projects.
Next principle.
Principle 17.
Resolve issues at your level. Don't ask
your sponsor senior stakeholders for
help solving problems on your project.
They hire you for that. I added this in
here. Remember guys, don't go out, you
know, don't go one of one of the popular
choices of the four choices on your test
is always to ask your PMO or ask your
sponsor for help. Never ask your sponsor
for help to solve people problem, vendor
problems, basically most problems,
you're not going to actually very rarely
that thing is ever the answer.
when it is the answer when will you ask
your sponsor your senior managers your
CEO for help is generally for an
approval
escalate only for approvals or authority
limits in other words push it up if
there's an authority limit that's met in
other words you need an approval to get
this done to add this to the project
that's a point sponsors senior managers
particularly sponsors are just there
really to approve things. They're there
to say whether they like this or
dislike, not to solve problems on a
project. It's no question on this one.
Question 17.
Your project team has been experiencing
low morale due to unclear roles and
responsibility and frequent
miscommunications between development
and testing teams. Team members has been
coming to you with complaints about each
other. Productivity has declined and you
can see tensions during team meetings.
Your sponsor mentions during the latest
status meeting that they have heard some
concerns about team dynamics. All right,
they're complaining. All right, the
productivity is declining.
Hey, ask your sponsor to step in and
clarify roles and expectations since
they have more authority.
First of all, don't do this. Managing
the team is on you. This is within your
authority limits.
Facilitate team meetings to clarify
roles, establish communication
protocols, and address interpersonal
issues as a project manager. I think
this is good. I like that. Recruit your
sponsor to bring in HR represent to
mediate. Once again, you're going
outside. You're asking for help here.
Escalate to senior leadership. No, this
is problems within the team itself. This
is something that you should be fixing.
You shouldn't have to give it away to
other people.
Now I want to point out to you guys here
guys you know when it comes to managing
when it comes to your exam anything that
manages the team is within your
authority problems on the team team
fighting with each other that's on you
don't escalate that up now speaking
about the team let's get into the next
set of um principles team leaderships
and collaboration here we get 18 to 27
principles. Got quite a lot here. Let's
go into this.
And the first principle is principle 18
here guys. What are we talking about?
Principle 18. Be a servant leader. This
is the theme of the PMP exam is to be a
servant leader. Now, this video is not
to go over all the specifics of servant
leadership. I want you to take my 35
hour course and watch that there.
But being a servant leadership is, you
know, one of the phrases I use is fetch
food and water. Being a servant
leadership is is about giving the team
they need to be successful, providing
and supporting them. So when I say fetch
food and water is giving them the
resources, I mean you could get them
coffee and donuts. That's food and water
somewhat. Uh get get them the resources
they need and support them. Don't
dictate to them. A servant leader is
very different than a traditional leader
that's more dictative. They are very
like do it my way or the highway type.
Servant leadership values the team
opinion, lets them work, stays away from
them while shielding them from
interruptions. Make sure you review
servant leadership principles in the
course.
What are we doing? Once again, we're
empowering. We're supporting the three.
We're going to be listening. We're going
to be coaching them and encouraging
them. We're not dictating to them. Maybe
we will value their opinions. Let's do a
question on this one. By the way, be a
central figure, not a dictator. Said
that.
Now, I do want to point out something to
you that we mentioned quite a few times
is always
allow a team to resolve problems. Don't
you should never select a
an option like if there's a problem on a
team and there's like multiple options,
work with the team, but you shouldn't be
the one just selecting it. And again,
don't be a dictator.
All right, practice question here.
Question 18.
Your development team has been
struggling with complex technical
challenge for the past week and team
morale is low. You notice that junior
developers seem hesitant to speak up
during technical discussions and one
team member mentions that they feel out
of their league with the current
requirements. What should you do? Take
charge of the technical challenge
yourself by researching solutions and
providing specific
direction to each team on how they
should implement your finding. No good.
This is more of being a dictator than it
is being a good project manager here. Uh
be that being a servant leader because
you're dictating everything. You're
fixing it further.
Bring in senior consultant to solve the
technical problems quickly and show the
team the correct approach. This is not
good. If you're bringing in something,
you're not empowering the team. you're
empowering somebody else to tell the
team what to do.
Organize peer programming sessions
between senior junior developers.
Schedule individual coaching sessions to
understand each other's concern and
celebrate small technical wins along the
way. I like this.
This is not bad. Peer programming is
when you put people together to work
together. One writes the code, one
checks the code. You are coaching them
individually. It's not a bad answer.
reassigned complex or once again you're
totally solving it to senior while given
simpler task
you know C is not the best best answer
but is the best here you A B and D
you're taking charge and you're fixing
the problem for them and this one here
you're more working with the team to
solve the issue making that one the best
answer now we want to understand that
this here is this is going to be a
common thing throughout this exam
servant leadership can't emphasize this
enough make you know the principles of
it. Review the course for that.
Principle 19. Act as an integrator, not
just a functional lead. You have to
integrate all the different components
of a project. Understand this. A project
is not just all about the scope or all
about the budget, all about the
schedule. Finishing something too quick
might lead to quality issues. Finishing
the entire scope may cause massive
overruns. finishing something really
cheap can cause components of the scope
to be out or comp or the time to just be
compressed for too long. So keep in mind
as an integrator you're just not looking
at one component of the project you're
looking at many components of the
project. So keep this in mind as you go
through the questions
question. Let's take a look at a
question on this question 19.
Your enterprise software implementation
project involves multiple work streams,
data migration, business process
redesign, user training, and system
configuration. Each team is progressing
well individually, but you're noticing
potentials potential integration issues,
timeline conflicts, scope misalignments,
and missing requirements, dependencies.
What should you do first?
Hey, focus on the areas
that's farthest behind schedule and help
the team catch up before addressing the
integration issue. All right, so notice
you're focusing on areas that's far
behind. All right, convey an integration
plan with all works uh all work stream
leads to identify start that again.
Convene an integration planning session
with all work stream leads to identify
dependencies, resolve conflicts, and
align timeline across all areas. Okay.
Okay, that's not bad because you're
looking at all areas working with
everybody. Delegate the integration
issue to each functional team and ask
them to coordinate directly with each
other to resolve conflicts. This is not
a good answer
in this one. You're pushing it off and
telling the team to solve it without you
being one of that central figure. A is
also not a good answer because you're
just concentrating on one thing.
Escalade to the sponsor. Never give away
work to the sponsor. We say that I'm
just done reading that. The best answer
here is going to be to bring everybody
together.
Work with everybody and prioritize
everything instead of one. Remember,
don't concentrate on one. Concentrate on
many things because a project is not
just a single component. It's many many
components.
Before
I get into this principle, uh, if you
guys are enjoying this video, can you
give the video a like? Did you subscribe
to the channel yet? I'm going to ask you
every 10 principles. It would greatly
appreciate it. Does take a lot of work
to put this together and my legs are
hurting right now. I've been standing up
for more than an hour.
So, if you don't if if you like the work
I'm doing, I would love if you could
give this video a like. By the way,
share it in your network. Would be
amazing, too. Principle 20.
The team is best suited to break down
work. Not much more to say here. The
team are subject matter experts. They
know the work better than all of us.
They're the best ones to tell us, for
example, what are the steps to paint in
this room. The team ask a painter that
your team. They're going to they're
better to better equipped and
knowledgeable to tell you the steps to
paint a room. A painter is the best
person to ask to paint a room. what are
the steps than anybody else. So ask them
to break down work. Let's do a question
on this.
Your project has received approval to
proceed with the next phase. Developing
a new inventory management module. You
have the highle requirements and need to
create a detailed work breakdown
structure for planning and estimation
purposes. But your development team
wouldn't be available for detailed
planning discussions for another week.
What should you do? Wait for the
development team to become available and
then have have them create the WBS
together even though it will delay the
planning process by a week.
Create a detailed WBS based on your
previous experience with similar modules
to keep the project moving forward. Then
review it with the team when they become
available. Now, I don't like this option
here because you're breaking down work
by yourself. Who says you have enough
experience to do this, right? All you
have is high level. Assign the W. A is
not bad here. Wait for the team to
become available. Okay, A is not so bad.
Assign the WBS creation to the technical
lead since they have both technical
expertise and familiar with the current
system. Okay, not not too bad. Create a
high level WBS based on UX and then then
have the team provide detail as uh when
they're available.
Very good answers.
We got to break it. We got to come down.
We got to start eliminating choices
here. What are we going to go with guys?
So we got assign to a technical lead.
We're just giving this away. I think the
team would be best just than the
technical lead. So now we e e e e e e e
e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e e
e e e e e e e e e e e e e either we're
going to create a side of a framework on
your experience and then have the team
provide the detail or we're going to
wait for the team. What are we doing? I
think the best thing here
is let's leave it to the team, right?
Let's make sure the team is best. Uh
it's you know what's good for us is not
to get involved especially breaking down
work. Notice in this one here we're
doing the high level framework and then
have the team provide detail. But what
if our highle framework is wrong? What
if we didn't put provide the high level
framework correctly, right? Why don't
you have them review it instead of
having them just break it down? Okay,
have them create the WBS together even
though it will delay the planet because
the team knows best. Make it a the best
answer. Always remember guys, the team
is the subject matter experts, not us.
All right, principle
21.
The team should should determine the
activity timing. So the team determines
how to break down the work, but the team
also can tell you how long work should
take. The best person to tell you how
long to paint a room is the painter.
They'll know, they're the best person to
tell you that, you know what, 200 foot
room like this or 4,000 foot room, this
is how long it takes to paint. So always
ask your team for the duration
estimates. They're the best ones to give
you that. Let's take a look at a
practice question on this.
You are developing the project schedule
for a website based on your experience
with similar projects and discussions
with the client. You believe the optical
sequence would be design mockups then
content creation followed by development
and finally testing. What you do
regarding the activity sequencing? So
activity sequencing if you remember from
the course is part of schedule
management. So what should we do first?
Should we do the design then content
development testing? All right. What
would be the best regard to sequence?
Identify which of these delayed
activities are on a critical path and
would actually impact the end date. Then
prioritize those.
Seems to me like you're doing the work
there. Present your proposed sequence to
the team and then ask and provide D time
estimates for each phase based on your
recommended approach. Okay. All right.
You're going to the team a little bit.
Share the project requirements with the
team and ask them to determine the
sequence and time it. I like this one
better. Not giving them the work. Let
them do it. All right. You're giving
them the work so they can use their
expertise. Create the schedule based on
your experience but remain flexible to
modify the sequence if the team
identifies any technical constraints. I
think the best answer here, guys, is of
course going to be work with the team to
do it.
In this one, you're doing all the work.
In this one, you're doing half of the
work. Uh, in this one, you're doing
still some of the work. Let the team do
it. They're the best ones to determine
how long work should take.
Next principle is going to be understand
team motivations to inspire performance.
A demotivated team is one of the best
ways to kill your project. A demotivated
team is one of the best ways to tank
your entire project and go down the
gutter. So, you don't want that.
We have to consistently on a consistent
basis motivate the team. We did cover
different types of motivational theories
in the course. Make sure to review them
like Maslo's hierarchy of needs,
McGregor's theory, XR. Make sure you
know those theories for your exam. But
on your practice questions, on your
scenario questions, on your exam, make
sure to keep your team motivated. Let's
do a practice question on this.
Your team's your project team's
performance has been declining over the
past month.
You've noticed that Sarah, usually your
most productive developer, seems
disengaged and is producing lower
quality work, appearing quiet and
distract distracted during team
meetings. What should you do first
before implementing performance
measures? All right, so this is not
good. All right, Sarah, usually
productive, very disengaged. What are we
going to do? Implement the performance
measurement
improvement measurements immediately
since decline in performance affects the
entire project and waiting could make
things worse. This is just forcing
things. Schedule a private conversation
with Sarah. Discuss what's affecting her
motivation and and engagement with the
project. I like that. Let's talk with
her. Assign Sarah to less critical task
until her performance improves to
minimize project risk while she works
through her issues. Help her. First
thing to do is just don't reassign. Just
don't fire people like that. Work with
them first. Discuss Sarah performance
decline with the team. So, this is a
problem here with Sarah and you don't
want to just go to the team to do it,
right?
Uh the best answer is of course going to
be meet with her. You don't want to just
discuss her. It's her performances. Talk
with her. Don't take away her work.
We're not sure why she's having this.
And just don't ignore her and just keep
on going. So, always work with the team
there. Team motivation is important not
just for your exam, but it's also
important in real life.
Not much to say here. Don't lie. Don't
cheat. Don't steal. Don't break the law.
I want to point out something to you.
Part of the mindset, and I'm telling you
guys a principle here.
Don't stop projects. Never stop a
project unless you're breaking the law.
Unless you're committing something
illegally. Okay, that's the key here.
Ethics stands above everything.
Everything. Okay,
following the law, for example, stands
above what your company is doing. If
you're working on a project and you
notice this project will be breaking the
law, stop the project. All right?
Because the you shouldn't be breaking
the law. Always be truthful. Even if
that truth means that you're probably
going to be fired, even if the truth
means that you're probably going to be
kicked off the project or the project is
going to have major issues going
forward, the test will test you on this.
Ethics is a topic on the exam objectives
and you will get questions on it. So
even though and they're not going to
make this easy because what they're
going to do is they're going to give you
choices where it seems like well if I
stay ethical the whole world is going to
end. Well, let the world end and you
stay ethical. That's the point of the
question to test your ethics. Let's do a
practice question on this.
During your software implementation
project, you discover that a team member
has been inflating their time reports,
claiming eight hours of work on days
when they're only presenting four to
five. This is actually against the law
by this stealing from company's time.
This has been going on for about three
weeks and your manager hints that major
time and your manager hints that major
time sheet issues are common. What
should you do?
So the manager does tell you that this
is probably a common thing. I don't know
if that's minor or not. I mean that's
about 3 hours they're building for him.
What should you do? Address the time
sheet issue directly with the team
member and establish clear expectations
going forward while documenting the
issues and corrective actions. Not like
this. Okay, you're taking you're taking
action against it. Overlook the time she
discrepancies. Team member is
technically competent and the project
can't afford here. You're letting the
ethical problems keep on going. That's
the problem here. Quietly discuss the
solution with other members to verify
the information before taking any
actions. This is a problem with one
person. Don't bring it to everyone.
Focus on the team member's deliverable
quality and productivity rather than
time tracking since the results matter
more than no there is a ethical problem
going on. This person is literally lying
on their time sheet and you have to take
it you have to fix this on your project
and the best answer here is going to be
a it's the best of the four choices. So
always stay ethical. Remember something
guys your objective in this exam is to
be ethical at all times. Again, doesn't
mean if the project gets stopped,
doesn't mean if you lose your job or
somebody loses a job at the world ends,
always be ethical.
Next principle, create a safe
environment for disagreements. Conflict
can be constructive, not just
destructive. Most people see conflict as
a destructive thing.
And while that is true, conflicts tells
me something. Let me tell you guys
something.
For two people
to have an argument, it tells me
something interesting about them. They
care about the problem. They care about
the issue at hand. I'll give you an
example.
When me and my wife were remodeling our
kitchen and the color of the cabinets,
in the center of the kitchen, she put
like this island. She has like this blue
island. All right. Now, she came to me
and she's like, "Well, we're going to
have white cabinets and she's going to
have put a blue island." And I'm like,
"Okay,
sure." Cuz I don't care. But she cares a
lot. Was there any arguments on the
color? No, because I really don't care
about the color of cabinets. Like, that
to me doesn't matter. I don't know why
this doesn't m but my daughter and my
wife had many discussions on the back
and forths
of what was the best color and then the
two of them came up and they got this
like light blue thing makes it happy.
The point of this is
when there are disagreements on this
don't look at it as a negative thing.
Sometimes the best solutions,
the the optimal solutions comes from
when people have disagreements between
each other because that's when a person
that believes this is the right way,
another person believes this is not the
right way. This is when they puts their
head together and create the best
solutions generally for the project or
in my project the color of the cabinet.
But when you have stakeholders that are
disengaged and ah I don't care about
that. No, that shows this stakeholder is
not particularly engaged in this. This
is not something you want in particular,
especially on senior stakeholders. So
remember that conflicts, yes, I know,
can be disruptive. Your job as a project
manager is to create a safe environment.
In other words, we want conflict. We
want people to care. The problem here is
if you have conflict and you crucify
them or you punish people, then they
will never have conflict. For example,
if you see two team members having a
disagreement and you penalize both of
them, they will never nobody will ever
fight again on your project and there
wouldn't be much conflict to come up
with good solutions. So create this safe
environment to let them know
disagreements are welcome and we want to
hear it and we want to manage it. Your
objective is to make sure that the
conflict stays at level one, level two.
In other words, it's very manageable.
Information is flowing freely, everybody
understands everybody. Not to level
five. And your job is to make sure it
never hits level five. You know, level
five conflict is when people physically
want to kill each other. So, you don't
want that. Good one. Highly on your
exam. Many questions on it. Let's do a
practice question on this
question. During a design review
meeting, you notice that whenever the
senior architect presents ideas, the
junior team members remain silent and
simply not in agreement. even when you
can see puzzles expression on their
faces. After the meeting, you've heard
two junior developers privately express
concern about the proposed architecture.
All right. What should you do to improve
team dynamics? So, they're not speaking
up like here like during the meeting
here. All right. So, what are we going
to do? Schedule individual meetings with
the junior members to gather their
technical input privately. Then present
their concerns anonymously in future
meetings. All right. Establish ground
rules for meetings that encourage
questions and alternative viewpoints and
model constructive disagreements by
respectfully question ideas yourself. I
like this because now you're bringing
them in. Now you're encouraging
questions. In the previous one, you see
in a I don't like this because what
you're doing in a here is you're keeping
it to the back burner again. You're
meeting them privately and then you're
doing anonymously.
You're not having much disagreements
here.
Ask the senior architect uh to to be
more open to questions and input from
junior members during design. Okay, I
like that. That's not bad. Rotate the
meeting and leadership. So the junior
team members take turns presenting their
ideas and leading technical discussion.
Now the best answer here is definitely
going to be B. It's better than C in
which case senior architects are just
taking more or just having people
rotate. If people are rotating, you're
still not opening up the environment so
everybody gets a say in it. They can be
the best answer.
All right. Next principle here, guys.
Protect your team's focus by avoiding
task overload. This is one of those
principles
where you don't want to overload the
team. You don't want to have the team
work overtime. You don't want to push
the team to do something that's going to
make them work overtime. Overtime is
unsustainable.
Task overload is unsustainable and will
lead to poor quality performance. Never
select an option like that. Let's see
the questions on this.
Your web development project is
progressing well when the marketing
director approaches you with an urgent
request for your lead developer to
quickly create a promotional landing
page for an upcoming trade show. Okay.
The lead developer is already working at
full capacity on critical project
features, but you're the only team
member, but they're the only team member
with specific skill set needed for this.
So, you got a team member already doing
work. Okay, what do we do? What should
you do? Ask the lead developer to take
on promotional landing page since it's
only a few hours and could benefit the
company significantly. You're making the
mark over time here. I wouldn't do this.
Negotiate with market to delay the
promotion land until after the current
sprint is complete. Okay. Have the lead
developer train another member to handle
promotional work. If you do this, you're
taking away work from them. You're
giving them additional work. Discuss a
request with lead to understand the
capacity and decline if it would
compromise their focus on the primary
project responsibilities. So in this
particular one here, what you want to do
is you want to work with them. So let's
combine all the principles. Let's work
with them.
Um, you don't want to just delay it
until after the current sprint. This is
something that you want to just bring it
to their attention and say, "Hey, can
you do it? If you can't, that's okay. If
not, let's move out." Then decline if it
would compromise. So, this one here,
we're working with a team. We're giving
the team what they want instead of being
a dictator and just decide, hey, no,
we're not going to just do that off the
bat. This is the best answer here
because we're not selecting for them.
We're letting them choose and we're not
task overloading them.
Principle 26, use prior programming for
skill development. Now, this is going to
be a tricky one in this principle
because you you don't have the expertise
to train people. You're going to have
the team to help train each other. In
the world of extreme uh programming,
generally there's this thing called peer
programming where one person writes the
code while one person checks the code.
For that to happen, they must be experts
at it. So, we're not talking about peer
programming here. I wanted to put wanted
to point that out. We're talking about
like a senior training a junior. Uh
we're talking about a guy a senior guy
that knows one thing training another
senior guy that doesn't know that thing.
Things of that nature. Let's see the
practice question on this. A project
manager is leading a data analytics
platform implementation when the team
realizes they lack sufficient expertise
in the new analytics tools. Three team
members have basic knowledge. Two have
intermediate skills and one has advanced
expertise. The team needs to develop
these skills quickly to maintain project
momentum.
What should the PM do? Enroll the entire
team in formal training course to ensure
consistent
uh skill levels. Well, do you need to do
the whole team? All right.
The team realized that they lack
expertise that some have basic, some
have intermediate, some has expert
skills. All right. Uh since not
everybody here, some people so I don't
know if I want to put all of them in in
the course. Organized peer learning
sessions team members learn teach and
learn from each other. Okay. Hire
additional members with the required
expertise. I don't think I would do this
yet because we have people with
expertise already.
Outsource the analytics components to an
external vendor. No, we have some people
that are experts at this. I think the
best answer here is going to be be let
them work and learn from each other.
It's okay to have team members learn
from each other and work with each
other. Sometimes that's your best
principle.
Now, I got this pretty cool principle
here. And this one is going to eliminate
so many choices for you. So, so many
choices for you. I call this the be nice
principle
on a project. This is eliminating. This
is not to select the right answer.
These things here, these things here are
all we're going to be using
to eliminate choices. For example, don't
fire anyone. If one of the choices like
remove this guy to this task, hire
somebody else, not not an answer, don't
make anyone over time. Just said that.
Don't put anyone down in front of
others. We just said that. If you have a
problem with someone, work with that
particular person.
If one person is causing issue, don't do
anything until you speak with that
person. All right? If one person is
interrupting a meeting, one person is
being mean to another person. All right?
uh don't do anything. Meet with that
person. See what the issue is. There's a
common question where people this guy's
always coming late to the meeting.
Always late. What are you doing? When
somebody's always late to a meeting,
you don't know why. Maybe they were
meeting with the CEO. Every day you have
this meeting. Maybe this person has a
health problem. Meet with them and
understand what that problem is first
before taking some kind of action.
All right, let's do a practice question
on this. Be nice principle. Remember
this principle is really to eliminate
options.
Question. A project manager notices that
one team member consistently arrives
late to meetings.
Interrupts others during discussion and
submits deliverables past agreed
deadlines. This behavior is affecting
team morale and project progress. Other
members have started making comments
about the individual's performance
during the meetings and some have
approached the project manager
requesting action. What should you do
first? Address the performance issues
with the individual in a private
one-on-one conversation. I like this.
All right, let's meet with them. Let's
find out what's going on. Discuss the
team members during the next team
meetings. Now, this is going to be in
front of everyone. Document the
performance issues and escalate to human
resources for disciplinary. Don't give
it away. Let's meet with them first.
Reassign the problematic. Don't fire the
guy. So, you notice this here is like
this principle really eliminates like
don't fire people. Don't give away your
work. not in front of everybody else.
Just work with that person. Make it a
the best answer. So remember, I think
that principle is really going to
really, really eliminate. It doesn't
allow you to select the right option
right away, but it eliminates some of
those bad choices.
Next thing here, guys, we're looking at
is going to be
agile specific principles. We got a few
of these here to go over. By the way, if
you're enjoying this video and you
appreciate that my legs are hurting
right now to get you to pass your exam,
you're going to click on that like
button, subscribe to the channel would
be absolutely amazing.
Let's get this
principle 28. The product owner
documents and prioritize features. Only
the product owner prioritizes the
product backlog. Train them if needed,
but don't do it yourself. This is
important.
At no point on an agile project. By the
way, let me stop right here. How do you
know when it's an agile project versus a
traditional project? Look for the
keywords. If you're working on a project
and you see the keyword like backlog,
product owner, sprint, iteration,
scrum, scrum master, you know you're
working on an agile project.
The real issue sometimes is it's when it
says hybrid. Hybrid is a tricky thing
because a hybrid project has a project
management plan and it has a product
backlog. So those you're going to want
to read very carefully. Let's go back to
this principle.
So I want to point out something. At no
point should you the project manager add
to the product backlog, remove things
from a product backlog or prioritize
things in a product backlog. Only the
product owner does that. All right,
remember that. Only a product owner does
that. Now there are going to be times
when the product owner does not want to
add sometimes the product owner be like
oh you know all of them are
uh highly valuable and they don't want
to prioritize it or they don't want to
this feature I don't know if I should
add it or not they have to determine
they have to determine if they want to
add it or they don't want to add it we
got to get a decision it's not something
we or the team should be doing the
product the product owner basically owns
the product backlog
question. Your agile development team is
starting the next sprint planning
session, but the product owner has been
traveling, hasn't had time to properly
document the user stories for the
upcoming features.
The development team is eager to start
working and has already identified
several features from the previous
discussions that they believe are high
priority. What should you do?
Allow the development team to start
working on the features that they
identify as high priority while the
product owner completes the
documentation in parallel. Okay.
All right. Notice you're letting them
work on the features that they identify.
So that the team here is doing basically
the product owner work. All right.
Probably not the best answer here. Okay.
Have the development team create the
initial user story documentation based
on their understanding. No good. The
user stories are called user stories
because there should be made by the
users not the team. Postpone sprint plan
to the product can probably document or
prioritize even if it creates a delay.
Okay. All right. Not the best answer.
Um
not the best answer, but it's okay. Work
with a product owner to quickly
prioritize the most critical features
and have them document just those
stories needed to start the sprint.
Okay, we got two decent answer here.
Which one sounds best? Well, I would say
let's not postpone anything. Can we get
the product owner to quickly prioritize?
Can we get some of those things in there
to get the sprint going? D and C and D
are decent answers, but D is just a
better answer. starts the work without
delaying the project and
it priorit it prioritizes it and it
documents what the team needs to start
doing the sprint plan making D the best
answer. Don't forget that the product
owner owns the product backlog. All
right, let's go with a one principle
that I just put a whole lot of things
into.
Is this the way agile team likes to
work? First of all, collocations. What's
a collocation? Agile teams love
collocation. Collocation is when you
bring everybody together in one central
place to work. It's different than
virtual teams in which case they just
work in silos. Agile prefers teams to be
together and work together in person
working. There are virtual collocations.
The way you would do that is by
basically having everybody use things
like Zoom, but everybody keeps the
cameras and mics on all day long. kind
of like each everybody's sitting around
a desk
on your exam. Face-to-face communication
is the most effective way to communicate
anything. Would you guys think this
video would be highly effective if you
never saw me and all you see was me
talking behind a slider? Do you think
it's effective? Because you can see me.
I can't see you, but you can at least
see my face. You can see my emotions.
You can see all my talking with hands
stuff. keeping you all engaged.
Face-to-f face communication keeps
people more engaged. Humans, believe it
or not, like seeing humans, not every
human, but most humans. In the course,
we did do a chart on this. There are
psychologists that said face to face
with a whiteboard is the most effective
way. Agile teams like wallspace.
Remember the term I used in the course?
High-tech, low touch. Let's use sticky
notes. Let's use magic markers. Let's
use whiteboards for your team.
Information radiators. So when you walk
into an agile space, you should see
automatically what they're working on.
This are going to be things like a burn
up and a burndown chart, generally on a
big screen or on a big chart somewhere.
Uh tell us what's what's left, what
they're working on. A good example of
this would be like a canband board. I
use cananband board. I use scrum band
personally when I do agile projects. and
a cambban board if I could just look at
a canband board and see hey they
finished that
still working on that and they have
those things to do so it is a great
amazing way to track what's the work in
progress what has been done what needs
to get done so can board is a good
information radiator remember something
agile will emphasize visual workflows
agile wants consistent
uh stakeholder inputs, customer inputs
and the sprint review meetings and they
break works up into iterations. So quite
a lot of things here with agile.
Let's take a look at a question.
Your New York's your agile development
project has team members distributed
across three different locations in New
York City.
The team has been working remotely using
video calls and collaboration tools. But
you've noticed communication delays and
coordination challenges affecting sprint
velocity. Sprint velocity is how much
work they're doing, how fast they're
doing work. What should you do to
enhance? Invest in better video
conferencing technology and
collaboration tool to improve the remote
working. Okay. Arrange for team members
from different location to travel and
work together in the same location for
the most critical aspect. I like that.
Okay. Okay, you're bringing people using
a collocation. It's going to be face to
face. All right. Establish more frequent
check-in meetings and structured
communication to improve more check-ins,
more communication. I think this is
going to lead to more problems.
Reorganize the work to minimize
dependencies
between different location. Allow each
site to work in. No, they should work
together. You're not bringing them
together. You're you're splitting them
apart. So, what do we do? Do we invest?
Do we go keep going the path of
technology or do we go low tech
highouch? Let's bring that collocation.
Now if you're thinking
isn't this a problem? Well, the question
has something very particular in it in
that it is in one city. So now if this
question was written where it was like
they were all over the world, then I I
don't think B would be a good answer.
Maybe A would have been a better answer,
but because they're in the same city, B
is probably a better answer than A.
All right,
next principle. And principle number 30.
Let's take a look at guys. Principle 30.
Uh, did you guys click on that like
button yet? Did you guys subscribe to
the channel? That would be amazing. Come
on, guys. My legs are still hurting. I'm
still standing up all morning. If you
guys can help me out because of my leg
hurting would be absolutely amazing.
Principle 30, roll out methodology
changes gradually using pilot or phase
implementation. So one of the things
you're going to get on your exam that's
pretty common is companies that are
changing. They're going from like
traditional to agile or vice versa or
agile to hybrid or something like that.
And do you just do this big bang
approach in which case you just push it
all on them and let them start working
in right away or do we slowly roll it
out? Well, in this mindset we're saying
don't push it all out. Sometime it
creates a lot of chaos. Let's see what
this is about.
All right.
Question 30. The organization has
decided to transition from traditional
waterfall project management to agile
methodologies across all development
teams. The CTO wants to implement agile
practices organizationwide immediately
to get benefits as quickly as possible
and has scheduled agile training for all
teams next month. What should you
recommend for implementing this
methodology change? support the CTO
plans to implement agile across all
teams simultaneously. After the training
to ensure consistent adaptation, quick
benefits realization.
This is going to create chaos. They
haven't really done this. Right after
the training, you push the whole thing
out. I'm not like I don't like that.
Select one to two teams to the initial
agile pro gather um lesson learn. Refine
the approach then roll out. Okay, I like
this. Not bad. All right, that's
following principle. Implement agile
only for new projects allowing current
projects to finish using traditional
then transition all teams once current
work is complete maybe
see I don't see C has a problem right
because you're waiting them and then uh
transition them once the current work is
done are you are you gathering lessons
are you looking to improve here I'm not
sure divide the team into groups and
implement agile phases first group
starts immediately after training.
Second group starts 3 months later. I
think the best thing here is to do the
gradual roll out. I think it's best to
refine the approach, gather lesson learn
versus just pushing it out now and then
three months later or just pushing them
in the moment their work is done. Let's
see and let's refine the process. You
know, I want to point out something to
you guys is
agile is different in every
organization.
Even though on our PMP exam uh agile is
you know this one is scrum or or it's
extreme programming or it's scandan or
something in organizations they they mix
it up and a lot of organizations has
their own little ways of doing things
and so in that sense B would probably be
the better answer
the next principle agile requires
ongoing customer feedback continuous
validation
the whole point of using agile is to
welcome changes is agile means to be
able to change, be able to move quick
and fast. We welcome changes on a
consistent basis and because of that we
welcome customer feedback. At least once
a month customer should be given
feedback on what was being made or is
made. Don't forget you have the sprint
review meeting where the customer gives
you feedback on what was done. So on a
consistent basis we're getting that and
you should always get this. Agile
promotes things like minimum viable
products for example. Let's go do a
question on this.
Your agile team has been developing a
mobile app for the past three sprints.
The customer was very engaged during the
initial requirements gathering but has
been increasingly difficult to reach for
feedback sessions. Missed to the last
two sprint reviews and saying they're
too busy to attend regular meetings. Oh
no. What should you do? Insist on insist
on regular customer feedback sessions
and adjust the sprint schedule if
necessary to accommodate the customer
availability even if it slows down
development. All right.
Continue development based on the
original requirements and the customers
expressed their trust in the team
and schedule a comprehensive review.
Probably not the best answer here.
You're just pushing them. You're not
getting their feedback.
Have the product owner make the customer
validation decisions based on their
business knowledge to maintain
development momentum. Not the best
answer. The best people to tell you
whether something is going right or
wrong is the people that's going to use
it. And that's the point of sprint
review meeting. Pause until the customer
becomes available for regular feedback
since agile cannot function effectively
without ongoing customer inputs.
Interesting answer. Interested.
uh you know one is pausing the
development, one is insisting on regular
feedback. You got two good answers here.
What are you going to go with? Well,
let's not pause development. You don't
want to stop a project just like that.
Let's see if we can get the feedback.
Even if we need to adjust some of those
schedule, it's better than pausing the
entire thing. So in this one, you're
adjusting the sprint schedule. In this
one, you're pausing development
completely. Which one is better? Let's
adjust the schedule or let's pause the
thing. And I think a is going to be the
best answer on this one. So we always
want to make sure that we gather those
customer feedback.
All right guys, let's take a look here
at the next set of principles. What do
we got here? We got quality and delivery
coming up right now. We got uh quality
is a is a major major player of customer
satisfaction. Poor quality leads to poor
customer satisfaction.
Good quality, higher customer
satisfaction. So let's see if you could
do this right.
Principle 32.
Define quality requirements early and
check them often. This is on a
traditional project. All right? And on
an agile project. Agile also uses this
concept of uh the definition of done.
So
quality requirements, I want to define
quality requirements versus scope
requirements.
Quality requirements is paint this wall
white.
Scope requirements is going to be I said
that wrong. Scope requirements paint the
wall white. Quality requirements are
things that's going to make the customer
not present, is going to be unhappy.
For example, you know, one of the the
quality requirements would be even
painted walls. You don't want to come to
one side as darker than the other side.
You don't want to paint over the guy's
light switch. Those would be like
quality requirements, right? You want to
make sure that you have nice even
painted walls if you're building this
phone. So, I just got a brand new phone.
I'm filming this video. I got this phone
a couple days ago. Here is the uh the
Samsung
uh I want to show you guys what's on my
screen here, but this is a here's the
Samsung
Fold 7. Now, this phone has a it's a
brand new style of phone. There's flip
phones and you can actually see that we
have a notch here, right, for when the
phone flips. Quality requirements for a
device like this versus scope
requirements. Scope requirements would
be of course that the screen functions,
it checks emails, it does everything a
smartphone supposed to do. But what
would make me upset? Quality
requirements would be like this crease
is too big and you can really feel it.
You really can't, by the way. You really
can't see it when looking at it. Quality
requirements should be how fast it
functions, right? So if I try to put my
thumb print and it takes too long to log
me in, the I would say this is a bad
phone. So one of the quality
requirements would be to make sure that
it has good performance. So remember
something quality requirements really
leads to customer dissatisfaction.
Score requirements is really what they
want. So we need to document this and in
the traditional projects those 49
processes we have something called
collect requirements. In that process is
where you document your quality
requirements and you store them in the
requirements documentation and then you
document how you will reach them in the
process of plan quality management. It's
in the quality management plan that you
will document how you how you plan to
meet the quality requirements on
traditional projects on an agile
projects. We will meet with the
customers and we're going to document
the quality requirements and how it
should function how it should look how
it should act when it's done by the
definition of done. For example, when
the product is finished making by the
agile team they're going to say how do
we know it's finished? Right? How do we
know we've actually met and produced a
high quality product? Well, that's what
the definition of done. All right, lots
of lots of things I said there. Let's
see the practice question on this.
Your team is starting development on a
new e-commerce platform. During the
initial planning meeting, stakeholders
have focused heavily on functional
requirements, but have provided minimal
guidance on quality standards.
respond respondent that we'll figure
that out as we go and just make it work
well. Uh that's probably not good.
Uh remember you notice the questionnaire
they're focused on functional
requirements minimum guidance on quality
standards. That's not good. What should
you do before development begins?
Proceed with the proceed with
development using industry standard
quality practices since the team has
experience and stakeholders trust their
judgment. Okay.
Begin development of core features while
scheduling quality requirements
discussions for later sprints when
stakeholders can see work and software
and provide more feedback.
Research similar e-commerce platforms to
identify typical quality standards used
for those default requirements until the
stakeholders provide guidance.
I don't love this one. I'm eliminating
this one. I like the others. Not I don't
really like them very well, but they're
better than C.
Facilitate discussions, facilitate
sessions with stakeholders to define
quality requirements, performance,
stability, usability, reli. Yes, this is
best. You know why? Because I want to
point out something to you that I didn't
mention is that quality is user
specific. Quality is is very subjective.
What I find that's quality, you don't
find quality.
So, we want to work with them. And you
really shouldn't start it until you
really know the quality here. So
definitely D is better than A and B. In
other words, A and B are waiting until
the work starts to start doing this. So
that would be the best answer. Don't
forget guys, quality is important. If
you do it wrong, you're going to have
bad customers and have to rework the
entire project.
Next principle. In traditional projects,
customers should validate deliverables
for scope and quality. Yes. You see in
the 49 processes we learned that there's
a process called control quality. In
that process the customers and you or at
least you go through the deliverable to
see if the deliverable has met the
quality requirements. That's how you get
the verified deliverable. In the process
of validate scope you would go through
the deliverables with the sponsor or the
customer to get a verified a validated
deliver or I'm sorry accepted
deliverable. The accepted deliverable
means it has met the scope requirement.
Now agile customer checks the quality
and scope during the sprint review
meetings. This is why you have them at
the end of every sprint. Show them what
what you built. Have them touch it, feel
it, use it, manipulate it. That's a
sprint review meeting. And hopefully I
mentioned earlier agile likes these
MVPs, these minimum viable products.
Agile says those are the greatest thing
in the world to have. When you have an
MVP, the customer can use it. They can
gain value from it. They can make money
from it. It's actually something that's
going to be installed on their computer,
for example, and they're going to tell
you what they like and what they don't
like. So, MVPs are great things to use.
Let's take a look the practice question
on this.
Your team has completed the first major
deliverable for your web application
project.
a fully functional user authentication
system. The system meets all technical
specifications and passes all automated
tests. But the customers been traveling
wouldn't be able to validate for
validation until the next phase until
the end of the next phase. What should
you do? Delay the authentication system
to production. Deploy the authentication
to production since it meets all
technical requirements and has passed
internal quality checks. Then get
customer afterwards. Okay. All right. I
don't know about that one. and you
disregard the customer. Continue with
the development phase while waiting for
a customer's validation since the
technical team is confident the
deliverable meets requirements.
All right. All right. Wait for the
customer to return and validate before
proceeding with the deployment or the
next phase. Okay. Okay. I kind of like
that. All right. I don't know about this
one here. I don't want to just push it
out here like that. Present the
authentication system to a customer
representative or proxy who can uh
preliminary validate until the customer
is ready. Okay. All right. So, we got a
couple of decent answer here. Which one
did you go with? All right. Do you want
to continue the next phase while
waiting?
All right. Uh
should we do that? Nah. I think we're
going to come down to either C or D
here. And the problem is notice wouldn't
until the next phase. So this is going
to cause a massive delay. The best thing
we need to do we need to gain some kind
of validation not just from our internal
system but from at least from a customer
or a proxy. So proxy people who can
choose on behalf of. So this is a better
answer than just waiting uh and delaying
it until the next phase. The point is to
make sure you get validation before
moving forward.
All right. You know, we want to I want
to mention this in uh agile projects.
When you are looking at quality on agile
projects when you're working with teams,
I did mention this earlier. You want to
use inclusive tools like whiteboards
rather than complex software. Always go
low tech, hight touch.
It's interesting how they built the
Empire State Building in the 1930s in
under two years and and we can't even
build a user interface on a piece of
software to all our high-tech machinery
in two years. Interesting, right?
Maybe we need to go back to this more
low tech and high touch. And I know I
know there's a bunch of AI stuff out
there. Maybe we can go back to low tech,
high touch and get work done be faster
and better. Let's
never on your exam choose options that
breaks the team apart. There is this
thing called silo work which case people
work by themsel. You don't want that.
You want people to work together not
separate from each other.
All right, let's take a look at a
question on this.
Your cross functional team needs to
brainstorm solutions for a complex
integration challenge that affects
multiple system components. The team
includes developers, business analysts,
subject matter experts, and stakeholders
with varying technical backgrounds who
all need to contribute ideas and
understand the proposed solutions.
What should you do to facilitate
effective collaboration?
All right. So, you notice
we got developers, we got analysts, we
got subject matter experts, we got a lot
of people working here. You want good
collaboration. What are we going to do?
Schedule a series of detailed technical
meetings where experts could present
comprehensive solutions using advanced
modeling software. Yeah, this this you
have a lot of people here, man. You have
BAS, you have subject matter experts,
you have developers, you even have
stakeholders. They all have different
backgrounds. I don't think people with
different technical backgrounds is going
to understand advanced modeling. So
digital collaboration where team members
can contribute ideas asynchronously
through structured templates and voting
mechanisms.
It's not bad but it's still very
technical right because it's a digital
platform
on it. Create a shared online workspace.
Real time editing capabilities. All
stakeholders can contribute. Okay, it's
not a bad answer. It's shared online
workspace. Not too bad. Let's see what
the other one is. Organize a workshop
where everyone can sketch ideas, sketch
ideas on a whiteboard. Yeah, definitely
the best answer if you're following this
principle because all of these are tech
tech. This is low tech making high
touch. Making that the best answer.
Humans like, believe it or not, I know
you guys have a hard time believing
this, but humans like being with other
humans. I know you don't.
Or sometimes I don't like being with
certain humans, but I like being with
certain humans. Like I like being with
my children. They're humans. Actually,
now I like being my dog. The Anyhow,
that's another story. All right, let's
take a look at the next principle.
traditional. This principle says use
bottomup estim estimating for more
accurate results.
When you are coming up with an estimate
of time and their cost, there are
variety of traditional estimates. You
got top down or analogous estimation
which is quick but not very accurate.
You have parametric. You have expert
judgment. The best estimate you can use
is bottomup estimation. Bottomup
estimation is when you break down work
into it details and then aggregate it
up. For example, this room is 200 square
foot. If I say, "How long will it take
to paint the wall?" You're going to say,
"Well, 200 square foot times 10 minutes
is 2,000
2,000 minutes." But is it really really?
Well, this wall has a whole bunch of
foam on it. This particular wall in
front of me because that's where all the
sound protection is in. This wall also
has a bunch of foam protection on it.
And this one has a door on it. So, these
two walls you don't need to paint. This
one has a door. So, realistically, that
wall zero time. this wall
uh let's say 25 minutes, this wall 25
minutes and this wall 50 minutes. This
is bottom up. So now you add up 50 50
you add it and you start to add up the
walls individually. So you break down
the work to the small then aggregate it
up. Now you have a perfect estimate.
Bottomup estimation
does require you to know the work in
detail and it does require a lot of
work. So it's takes long to do but it's
very accurate. When it comes to agile
estimation,
they use relative estimation techniques
like story points and planning poker. In
the agile course, I don't want to get
too much in depth because it's a big
discussion. But in the agile course, I
reviewed with you guys the Fibonacci
sequence, in which case they use the
Fibonacci numbers. Uh I can't remember
it right now. 1 3 I forgot. plus one now
one two then it's three then it's five
then it's eight something like this
right I can't remember it all right now
but you guys check out the Fibonacci
sequence I do cover that in the course
that's what they use they assign these
things every user story is given a
certain number then those numbers are
added up to form the entire points of
the product backlog the product backlog
let's say I got 10 stories each is worth
50 points it be 500 500 points to
complete this entire project. If you're
doing
uh 50 points an iteration, then it' be
10 iteration, be 10 months to do it.
That's how they do this. How do they
determine how much work they can do? By
doing the team velocity. Hopefully,
everything I said there made sense. If
not, you need to review the course again
because this you will be tested on
during the class, during the exam.
And of course, here in this video,
question 35. Your team needs to provide
time estimates for developing a new
customer portal with several integrated
modules. The project sponsor is asking
for accurate estimates to support budget
planning and resource allocations
decisions. What estimation approach
should you use? Use your experience from
a similar portal project and applying
scaling factors since historical data
provides reliable baseline estimates and
is much faster than detailed breakdown.
I don't think you should be doing this
because this is considered more of a top
down where you're just pulling from
historical data. Have technical leads
provide highle estimates for each module
based on your expertise since they
understand the technical complexity.
Okay, not too bad. You are bringing in
other people but it's high level. Get
detailed task level estimates from
developers who will perform the work.
Then aggregate those to create the
overall project timeline. This is better
because in this one you're breaking out
the work. Combine approaches by using
historical data for the initial
estimates
than having tech than having technical
leads validated. So this one here you're
pulling it from historical data. The
best answer here is going to be to have
those estimates uh come from the team
members themselves. C best answer. So
remember guys, the best form of
estimations are always top down.
The next part of this here guys is we're
going to be doing is going to be the
risks and procurement section of this.
We do have a few principles I want to
mention that comes to risk. Let's take a
look at it here. And this is going to be
principle 36. Now,
oops, push yourself a little bit. All
right, here we go.
When it comes to risk, let's just say
everything in life has risks. Pembach
defines risk. An uncertain event. Number
one, risk is uncertain. An uncertain
event that affects one or more project
objectives. Risk affects your project.
How does it affect your project? Well,
there's what's called positive risk
called opportunities. These are risks
that can reduce the schedule,
reduce your budget, increase
functionality.
Negative risks are risks that can push
up the schedule,
go over your budget, reduce
functionality,
like a bad snow, like getting a bad
snowstorm or a permit coming really
late, delaying your project. Positive
risk is where team members are extremely
come to find out extremely knowledgeable
in this can finish the work quicker.
Positive risk can be the permit coming
six weeks earlier. So we want to make
sure we understand that. Now we want to
document risk early and thoroughly. We
want to do this throughout the project.
Risk is not something that's done just
once. You want to do it early because
you never want risk to derail you. A
good project manager is able to predict
the risk and respond to these risks.
Question.
You started a new cloud migration
project for your organization's legacy
system. The sponsor is eager to begin
the migration work immediately and has
expressed concerns that spending too
much time on planning activities might
delay the benefits realization. What
should you do first now?
Conduct a comprehensive risk
identification session. Before beginning
any migration work, document the
potential technical issues and
organizational risk. Okay.
All right. Begin the migration with less
critical first to gain experience and
identify risk. Well, I don't want to
start the work right away. That's
probably not the best answer.
Start the technical migration. Again,
you're starting it without knowing your
risk. You shouldn't do the work if you
don't know the risk. Focus on technical
risk only. that uh since those are the
impact the cloud no I think here you
want to do your risk assessment
they want to do it but you you can't
start the work until you actually know
the risk because if you don't know the
risk that's going to affect your project
you might end up in a situation where
something happens and you don't know how
to respond and the whole thing gets
completely delayed and thrown off. If
you identify risk that you can put in
safeguards to even stop those risks from
happen them before they start. Remember
something everything in life has risks.
Now next principle
is document responses for both threats
and opportunities. I mentioned earlier
opportunities are the positive risks.
Threats are the negative risks.
The risk registers stores both negative
and positive risk. So I'm telling you
guys here the risk register is where you
store the risk the listing of the risk
and the responses. The risk management
plan doesn't have risks. So if they give
you a question and they say there's an
uncertain risk and one of the choices to
update the risk management plan risk.
Wrong. You don't do that because the
risk management plan doesn't have risk.
The risk management plan tells you how
to manage risk, but it doesn't actually
have risk in it. So, you don't you want
to make sure that you understand that
concept.
Let's do a question on this.
Your software development project is
progressing well when you receive
unexpected news. A major competitor has
just announced they're discontinuing
their similar product, creating a
significant market opportunity. So this
is a positive risk. Additionally, a key
technology event has offered you early
access to the new API that can enhance
your product capabilities beyond the
original scope. Oh, good. What should
you do first? Quickly modify the scope
to incorporate the enhanced API and
accelerate the market
positioning. I don't think you should
take an action right away without really
assessing it. See what's going on here.
Schedule emergency meeting to discuss
how to pivot the market project strategy
to capture the maximum benefits. Okay.
Okay. Not too bad. Document these
efforts in your risk register and
develop uh specific responses. Okay. I
like this. Begin. No, you shouldn't
implement right away. Don't take an
action right away. Now, it comes down to
two things. Should we document it in a
risk register? It is an opportunity. Or
should we go talk with the stakeholders?
Well, here's what I'm going to do. I'm
going to do C first and then I'm going
to do B. But it's asking what do you do
first? I can see the best answer here.
So remember something about risk.
Uh risk is something that is you know I
want to go back to a principle here. I
want to go back to this uh principle
when you're doing risk identifying
documents early and thoroughly. I should
I want to add in here. Let's add in
another point.
And you want to do this all throughout
the project. All right, you identify
risk. Let's add this in right on the fly
on the video. Risk is identified
continuously.
This is why I see I don't write man.
Best handwriting the world here guys.
Remember something about risk. I want to
mention that risk is consistently
evolving. Risk is consistently getting
better, getting worse. Remember
risk at a certain level today will
change tomorrow. Getting the flu in the
winter time is higher than getting the
flu in the summertime. So risk evolves
continuously. So you're always
continuously identifying and assessing
risk throughout the life cycle of your
project. At any moment new risk can
arise and old risk can go away. So your
risk register is a living document that
keeps on moving.
All right. Uh question and principle 38
question principle 38 let's go on to
vendor management use mutually
beneficial contracts and procurement.
Now this is important in the course we
covered different types of contracts
time material cost reimburseable and
fixedric contracts. The key though your
exam is not really going to say hey you
know what's the definition of that
contract. It's a scenario based exam.
What you want to do is you want to
identify when to use one over the other.
And you have to remember something. Time
material, use it when you don't know
your scope and the scope is very high
level. Cost reimburseable, use it when
you want to balance the risk between you
and a vendor. Fixed price contracts when
you know your scope really well and you
don't want to manage risk.
But I want to bring up this point here
that when when you're negotiating a
contract, you want a contract that
satisfies you and your vendor. Don't do
lopsided contracts, in which case it's
all for you and forget the vendor. So
this is more of an ethical thing, in
which case we're going to be trying to
be fair on every side.
38.
You're negotiating a contract with a
software development vendor for a
critical project component.
Your procurement team has drafted a
contract that includes steep penalties
for any delays.
Requires the vendors to accept unlimited
liabilities for any issue. That provides
limited payment milestones. What should
you recommend? Oh boy. I would not like
to work with this company. It's what I
would say if I was a vendor. Proceed
with the contract as drafted since it
maximizes protection for your
organization and the vendors already
agreed to the terms
and if I just want to keep doing that.
Modify the contract creat more balanced
risk sharing reasonable terms and
incentives that benefits both parties. I
like it.
Add additional penalty clause to ensure
vendors performance while maintaining
the current favorable terms for your
organization. I like that. It's not bad.
All right. You want to I like that
because if you hate your vendor, you
would like that even more. So, let's go.
All right. So, if I'm working with a
vendor I really hate, I'm probably going
to add more things on there. But
obviously, that's against the mindset,
guys. It's not go see. Accept the terms,
but add bonus. This is just adding a
little icing on top of your terrible
contract. The best thing here to do is
to be is to work with everyone.
All right? You have to be fair in what
you're doing.
All right, I got two more principle here
guys. Um on uh two principles that deals
with life cycle and closures. Let's get
into it. 39. Update the lesson learn
register throughout the project. Yes,
the lesson learn register.
The four of the 49 processes you have
something called manage project
knowledge. Lesson learn register is also
in your agile project. In agile they
have the retrospectives where they do
this. But remember something, you don't
update lesson learn once at the end of
this the phase or the project. You do
lesson learn. You update your lesson
learn throughout the entire project.
You learn something now, put lesson on
register. You learn something tomorrow,
put in the lesson learn register.
Now, oops, I missed something there.
Here we go. Uh, lesson learning lesson
on register. We just said that created
in the project in the process manage
project knowledge. All right, we did
actually say that. All right.
Question 39. Your agile development
project is halfway through when your
team discovers that the initial API
integration approach isn't working
requiring a complete technical pivot
that cost two weeks but ultimately led
to a much better solution. It's lesson
learned right there guys. Additionally
learned that conducting user train at
every three sprints instead of every
sprint actually provides better feedback
quality. More lesson learned. What
should you do to recording these
discoveries? Wait until the project
retrospective at the end to document all
the lessons learned comprehensively and
ensuring you capture the complete
picture of what worked and didn't.
Document these lessons learn
immediately. Sline register so they can
benefit
the current and future projects even if
it takes time from the current sprint
work. Share these insights uh informally
with other project teams through casual
conversation and team meetings. No, got
to put in lesson on register. Focus on
completing the current deliver first
then schedule dedicated time after the
release. Not after the release. This can
take a long time. So we're going to do
this retrospective. Let's do it
immediately.
I do want to point out that the agile
projects also have lesson learn and it
shouldn't take that much time away but
it's where learning things put it in the
put it in the lesson learn register and
then you can refer back to them in the
retrospective making that best answer.
Now I want to talk about when it comes
to closing your project in number 40.
Did you guys uh click on that like
button? You know my legs are really
hurting now. Now my hips hurt. Can you
guys relieve some of that pain by
clicking on the like button, subscribe
to the channel? If you already clicked,
don't click it again though. Principle
40. All projects should be formally
closed, whether completed successfully,
terminator or terminated early, ensuring
all bills are paid, and resources
released. Now, I want to talk about
closing this project here.
On this exam,
you're probably going to get a question.
I'm pretty sure you're going to get a
question where a project is unexpectedly
terminated. What do I mean by that?
You're working on a project, you're
halfway done, the CEO in the middle of
the night decides, "We don't want to do
that anymore. Kill that project." Calls
you up the next morning, kill the
project. We don't want to do that. What
do you do? And then he's like, "Go work
on this project." And then you're like,
you just leave this project and just go
work on the next one. No. Every project
needs to be formally shut down. This
includes when the CEO calls and says,
"Okay, we got to terminate that
project." Be like, "Okay, I need to do
this, this, and this. I need to make
sure I need to release the team members.
I need to pay all the bills. A project
cannot close. If there are bills that
needs to be paid, maybe you got
contracts and vendors that need to be
paid. You need to formally release team
members and tell them where to go. Did
it go back to operations? Did it go work
on a new project?
Um and you need to document what was
done, what wasn't done in the project
report. Remember this a document output
of closed project or phase. So you have
to formally close down all projects. Now
I do anticipate you guys getting a
question like this on your test.
Question 40. Your mobile app development
project has been cancelled due to
strategic changes in the organization.
The executive team wants to immediately
reassign all project resources to a new
priority in incentive that starts next
week, instructing you to wrap things up
quickly since there are no deliverable
to complete. H notice they won't
immediately reassign all the resources.
Uh, what should you do?
Immediately transition the team to the
new as requested. Handling the
administrator cleanup yourself over the
next few weeks.
I don't know. Request additional time to
properly close out contracts,
equipments, organize and conduct the
final uh final final financial
reconciliation. Okay. Assign one member
to handle the closure while moving the
rest of the team. One person. I'm not
sure. document the project status and
outstanding items and then hand over
closure to the operation. So notice
you're handing over the work. You're
handing over the work. You're just
terminating it. The best answer here is
going to be to formally close out that
project. Making that the best answer.
You must formally close out your
projects at all time, guys. You never
want to
you never want to just go on and do the
project just like that. Formally close
it out.
All right, let's take a look here, guys.
And the next section we got is
continuous improvement. Now continuous
improvement
is something that we should be doing on
a consistent basis with our projects.
Something that we're going to work on
quite a lot.
Uh if you don't continuously improve,
you will
become obsolete. You guys are
continuously improving, right? You're
taking your PMP. Let's take a look at
this principle. Repeat and reinforce the
vision to the team. Important.
As you're working on a project
and you're a team member, your head is
stuck in the screen, right? The screen.
So, I have a screen right here. Screen
of coding. All you're watching is code.
You tend to forget the long-term aspects
of where this project is going. You're
forgetting that this project supposed to
do this or supposed to accomplish this
and so on. That's the problem here. What
we want to do is we want to always as a
good project manager, we want to
consistently work with the team to let
them know what this vision is. Let them
know what this project is about. Let
them know what the what they're trying
to work on. Sometimes when you're
digging up the road and you're you're
just a worker digging up the road,
fixing a hole, you kind of forget that
the whole idea is to make sure it's nice
smooth paves with pipes fixed at the
bottom. So it's a good project manager.
We are going to work with them for the
to reinforce that project vision. Let's
take a look at a question here.
Your e-commerce platform project is
three months into development when you
notice the team has become highly
focused on technical implementation
detail and sprint deliverables. And this
is common. This is what I was mentioning
earlier. They become so ingrained in the
work they kind of forget the whole
picture. team member seems to have lost
sight of the bigger picture. Creating a
seamless customer experience that will
revolutionize how users interact with
the company's products. What should you
do?
Continue letting the team focus on
technical excellence
since they're making good progress on
deliverables and the vision will become
clear once they see the fi finished
product.
[Music]
You're not doing anything here. Don't do
nothing. It's part of if one of the
choices like just keep doing what you're
doing is probably not the answer. Bring
in the product owner to realign the team
with business requirements and ensure
techn is something that you need to do.
Don't bring in other people to help you
sponsor a product owner. Create a
detailed user story to explicitly
connect each technical task to specific
customer. You shouldn't be writing user
stories. Schedule a regular session.
Discuss and reinforce how the technical
work connects to the overall vision.
Yes,
let's work with the team. Let's bring
let's always show them that vision.
Let's continuously
uh keep preaching the vision so they
know where they are. I know I know this
sounds a little crazy, but it is very
easy to forget the long-term effort of
what you're doing when you're ingrained
in the work.
When you're working on a project, it is
important to clarify what success and
failure look like. It is critical that
you know
that success looks like this,
failure looks like this. In agile, we do
this thing called remember the future.
In which case, you work with the
customer to say remember the future.
Now, this sounds crazy. What is remember
the future? Well, it's an exercise you
do when you ask your um customer what
would a successful deployment of this
software look like? what a successful
user interface of this and they tell you
well it functions like this it had this
feature it did this it produced this
number it had this report now you're
they're telling you what success looks
like so we want to consistently do this
we want to clarify the team should
really understand and we're going to do
this with things like user stories
uh remember the future like I told you
about but then you also got to ask what
would cause this thing to completely
fail
they might tell you well it failed a
function like this it uh it was too
slow. It produced these errors. Now you
know what to look for. So on a project
we want to consistently do that. All
right, let's take a look at a practice
question here.
Your team is working on a customer
service automation project with the goal
of improving customer satisfaction.
However, during a recent discussion, you
realize that different stakeholders have
different interpretations. The VP of
customer service expects a 20% reduction
in support tickets. The IT director
assumes success means deploying the
system on time within budget. What
should you do to address this? Work with
all stakeholders to define specific
measurable criteria for project success
and failures. Ensuring everyone has the
same understanding what constitute the
goals. Yes, I like this. You're working
with everybody. You're getting what
success and what failure looks like. I
like that.
Continue high level goals since
stakeholder agreement on broad term is
more important. Don't do this one here.
You're not doing anything. Focus on
delivering the technical solutions as
specified. Since stakeholders
satisfaction with the deliverable will
naturally indicate whether the project
succeeds. All right. All right. Uh and
this one here you're focusing on one
thing. All right. I don't like that. I
think A is better. document the
different stakeholders expectation and
plan to address them through multiple
success criteria to satisfy. So we got
two good we got A and D. We're just
going to document them and plan to
address them through multiple or let's
all bring them together and let's come
up with what success and failure looks
like they can aid the best answer. This
is something that's important to
consistently do. It's really important
to understand what success looks like
and what failure looks like.
Quick one principle in agile
the retrospectives are used to review
and improve future sprints or
iterations. Same thing sprint iteration.
The retrospectives are done at the end
of the agile projects to understand what
we did right during the sprint, what we
did wrong during the sprint, what should
we do more of in the next sprint and
what should we do less of. It's where we
look back on
where we spent too long on meetings.
Maybe we spent too long collaborating
here. Maybe we were using the wrong
techniques here. Agile teams are always
looking to do continuous improvement.
And one of the best ways to do that is
in a retrospective. So remember, it's
done at the end of every sprint. We're
going to document what we should do more
of, what we should do less of, what we
should improve upon, what doesn't need
to be improved upon, and so on. So
remember, retrospective, you cover this
in depth. Make sure you understand.
Question.
Your agile development team has just
completed their third sprint and
delivered all committed features
successfully. Team velocity is
consistent, stakeholders are happy with
deliverables, and there are no major
blockers or conflict. Some team members
suggest skipping the retrospective this
time since everything went well
since they prefer to use the time of a
plan in the next sprint. Now, this is
something you don't do.
So, skip the retrospective since the
sprint was successful. Use the time for
more detail.
Something you should be doing, not
something you should be skipping.
Conduct a brief 15-minute retrospective
just to check if there are any issues.
Then move on to sprint planning. Okay.
Hold the full as planned. Focus on what
was successful in the sprint. Identify
opportunities for even better
performance. I like that more. Replace
with a celebration of successful. No,
no, don't replace it. Let's do the full
thing. Stick to the retrospective. The
retrospective is where we're going to
use to improve upon. Even if the team
feels there's nothing to improve, that
is incorrect. We can always get better
at what we're doing, no matter how great
we're doing it. Let the team know that
and proceed with the full retrospective
principle. Next principle,
implement feedback loop. Apply lessons
from one task to the next. So feedback
loop is when you're doing something and
a customer or team member tells you,
hey, that's great. um then take whatever
you did great and then apply it to the
next thing. Do it like that again or
make it better. Or the customer says,
"Hey, that isn't good." Then don't do
that again, right? Or fix it because
it's not good. Use feedback loops. So
feedback loops when I tell you
something, you apply that and I tell you
something again, you apply that again.
So it's a loop keeps on going and going.
This is expected throughout your entire
project. So it's something you always
want to implement.
All right, let's take a look here.
Question 44.
Your team has just completed the first
module of a multi-module
software system. During development,
they discovered that the initial
technical approach caused integration
challenges. The testing strategy missed
some edge cases and stakeholder reviews
would have been more effective earlier
in the process. What should you do
before starting the second module?
Analyze the lessons from the first
module and adjust the technical
approach, test and strategy and review
process for the second module before
development begins. Okay, I like that.
Begin mod development of the second
module as planned while document lessons
from the first to future reference. I
don't like this for future should be
using it right now. Continue with the
current approach since the team gained
valuable from the first. No, implement
what you learned. Schedule a detailed
postmodern review of the first to be
conducted after the second. You should
implement that right away. The moment
you see something is wrong. You and you
get feedback. Don't wait till the next
phase. Don't wait till the next
uh deliverable. Don't wait till the next
sprint. If you get if you find a way to
fix something right now, fix it right
now. Just don't push it off. Right?
That's something you want to do. Okay.
Principles 45 and 46. We're looking at
cost and schedule management. Two quick
principles.
Principle 45.
Avoid cost and time overruns
if if you must choose to fix budget
issues before scheduling. This is a
wider principle.
Obviously, you don't want time and cost
overruns, but if you got to choose one,
if you must choose, fix the budget
first. People are more worried about
money than time. It should be the
opposite. But go with me on this. If you
get a question, and I want to show you a
question like this. If you get a
question like this, stick with the time.
All right? And this is on a traditional
project. By the way, I'm sorry, stick
with fixing the budget first. This is on
a traditional project. on an agile
project.
Agile projects has what's called time
box. Each sprint has a fixed duration of
about two to six weeks
uh and is determined by the team
capacity. So the team determines how
much work they're going to do in each
sprint. All right? And they adjust the
scope within each iteration. What does
that mean? Well, remember the scope on
an agile project is consistently
changing. So that's something you want
to keep in mind.
So how do we work with um time and cost
overrun on an agile project? Well, first
of all, agile has a fixed budget and a
fixed schedule. So they will generally
adjust the scope within each iteration.
Sometimes they adjust the scope on the
project to keep the budget and time the
same because they have fixed duration.
If you remember the beginning of when I
taught agile, I said about flipping a
triangle. In traditional projects,
you're trying to keep the scope the same
while adjusting cost and time. Ideally,
you're adjusting more time than cost. In
agile, you're adjusting the scope to
keep the actual budget and schedule the
same. Let's do a question on this.
Your project is facing both budget
pressure and time constraints. Due to
unexpected technical complexity, you're
projecting a 15% budget overrun on a
three-week schedule delay.
What approach should you prioritize?
Focus on reducing scope and features to
meet the original project to meet the
original timeline accepting the budget
overruns as necessary. Cost of
maintaining the schedule commitment.
All right. Notice focus on reducing
scope and features. All right.
uh negotiate additional funding to cover
the budget overrun while accepting the
3-week schedule as a trade-off.
Implement cost reduction measures to fit
first to address the budget overrun.
Then work on schedule compression. All
right. Seek a balance approach that
partially addresses both issues. Accept
them smaller overruns in budget and
schedule rather than fully res fully
resolving either. So this is a tricky
question. You notice it's asking what
you going to prioritize. You got to
choose one. Should have reduced the
scope. One of the things especially this
is not an agile project. Doesn't state
it. It seems like it's a traditional. So
what are we going to do? Negotiate for
extra money. Are we going to cost do
cost reduction measures? Going to seek a
balance here. The best answer here like
I point out is to put in that cost
reduction measure in there. Let's reduce
uh the cost and then try to fix the
schedule around it.
When it comes to traditional projects,
you want to understand
when managing the schedule, we have
something called a critical path. I
don't want to get into critical path on
this because this it's a very long
topic. Understand for your exam that a
critical path is the longest
dur is the longest path through your
schedule or through your network
diagram. It determines the length of
your project. It carries the highest
risk activities. Any manipulation
of activities on the critical path will
result in the project extending or
decreasing. So if you want to compress
your schedule, compress the critical
path activities that will shrink the
schedule. If you're if activities on a
critical path are it has no slack,
right? Has no float. If activities on a
critical path are extended, the whole
project gets pushed out. Remember these
concepts for your exam.
Agile manages schedule two sprint
commitments and velocity. So once again,
let's go through this. On an agile
project, how do you determine the
schedule? Well, if the product backlog
is 600 points and the team does 100
points per iteration, the velocity is
how much points they do per per
iteration. Then you know you have six
iterations in this. If each iteration is
four weeks, it's a four uh it's a
six-mon project.
So that's how you would do this. All
right. Now, don't forget they also work
on the highest priority. So the way
their work is scheduled is based on the
highest priority work to the lowest
priority work. Very different than
traditional project where you're just
doing all the work in one big shot and
you're not breaking it up.
Let's do a question on this.
Your project has encountered several
issues simultaneously. The UI design is
running two weeks behind schedule.
Database optimization delayed by one
week. Security review has slipped by
three and integration testing four days
behind.
What should you focus on first when
assessing the schedule impact? Identify
which of these delay activities are on a
critical path and will actually
implement the project end date. Then
prioritize those. Okay,
I like that. Address the UI design since
it affects user experience and
stakeholder satisfaction.
Okay, I like this all because you're
trying to fix the schedule here. Focus
on security review since has the longest
delay and security issues could prevent
project deployment.
Work on all delays simultaneously. This
require too much resource since they all
behind schedule. I think the best answer
here if you want to fix your schedule
is you want to focus on a critical path.
You focus on a critical path. If you fix
the critical path or you reduce the
critical path, the whole schedule
compresses. So remember that concept for
your exam.
Coming down to the last of it, I just
got a few more principles I just want to
quickly go over with you. There's going
to be some quick principles. I probably
mentioned a few of these, but I wanted
to just to put them in here so you can
see them again. Uh, by the way, have you
enjoyed this video so far? We're coming
down to the end. Look, look how long it
is. See, I don't really know how long it
is because I'm just recording it up, but
uh it's it's pretty long, right? So, if
you guys enjoy the work I'm doing, give
the video a like. Share this video with
others. Would be amazing.
All right, let's go over this. I want to
point out a couple exam strategies when
you're doing your exam.
This principle here is not going to
apply in every single scenario or every
single question, but most 90% of the
questions. A couple things I want you
guys to know. When you see answers that
are absolute,
like always or all, they're not probably
correct. Like always implement this,
always work with this, always fire this
guy. Those are probably not going to be
the answer. Project management is never
absolute. The answer, you know, what's
best is dependent on the scenario. And
you're not going to do this thing all
the time.
So keep that in mind. All right. It's
not something that's always
okay
and stop. Answer this question without
looking at the answers. I'm sorry,
without reading the question. Answer
this one. So look, I'm not going to read
it. This one says always all never. I'm
going with C. It might or might not be
the answer. I don't know. But I'm going
to go with C. Let's see if this works.
Your project team is debating the best
approach for stakeholder communication
during a system implementation.
Different team members have varying
opinions about communications,
frequency, methods, and content based on
their experience with different types of
stakeholders. What statement presents
the best approach for stakeholder
communication.
Always communicate status regularly to
all stakeholders
uh to maintain transparency and keep
everyone engaged. Not every stakeholders
needs to be communicated regularly. CEO
probably not. Probably just wants to
know you start and when you're done.
All project decisions should be made
collaboratively. Not not necessarily not
all the time with stakeholders input to
ensure you're never going to get every
stakeholder to agree on your project. So
no tailor communication frequency based
on stakeholder specific needs. Yeah, we
did talk about this. The communication
should be tailored to the stakeholder.
Never make significant changes without
first conducting thorough you should you
should not make any changes without
assessing those changes making see the
right answer. Now once again
that principle
is to eliminate choices. The moment you
see something says all
never
uh something that is always the right
answer. Now, speaking about never, let
me put never in another term. Never do
nothing. It's easy as that. What do I
mean by that? Well,
never on your exam, choose a choice that
doesn't
change something, that doesn't take some
kind of action. If you're going to
choose,
if there is a choice that says continue
doing what you're doing, in other words,
you're doing nothing, don't select that.
So, never do nothing. All right? If a if
you read the choice and you're like,
"Well, they ain't doing anything. They
just continue doing what they're doing
right now." That is not the answer.
Let's see what I mean in the question.
Don't read, don't read the question.
Let's see if you can just go through the
answers.
Continue with the current development.
Focus on completing all the features.
Wait to address the API. Contact the
vendor to understand the issue. Which
one did you go? Choose one answer.
All right. And let's read the question.
See if you got it right. Choose one
answer. So continue with the current.
Focus on completing all their things.
Wait to address it or contact the vendor
to understand the issue. H. Which one
did you go with? I know what I went
with. Let's see if you got it right
because I know what I went with. All
right. Obviously, I can see the answers
right here. off. Uh your development
team has reported that a third-party API
the integrated with has been
experiencing immediate slowdowns over
the past week. The API vendor hasn't
acknowledged any issues and the slowdown
haven't caused hasn't caused complete
failure yet.
Just long uh just longer response times
that my user might notice. What should
you do? Okay, so we had a problem with a
with a vendor here.
They haven't they haven't acknowledged
any issues and the slowdown haven't you
know caused complete fail. What should
you do? Continue with the current
development. Well, no, because you know
it might cause an issue coming up later.
Focus on clean all the features and
revisit if it becomes an issue you
should fix. Be proactive. Don't be just
reactive. Wait to address it until the
sprint planet. If you're waiting, it
might collapse. So, I know I got D. Did
you get D when you read it? So I would
say contact the vendor. Let's fix this.
Let's be proactive on it. There was
something here. A, B, and C never really
did anything with it, but they just let
it kept progressing. They let kept
pushing it off, which is not the best
answer.
So always you want to be proactive,
right? You don't want to
uh you know, you always you you want to
be proactive. You don't want to just
leave things. All right. Here's the one
that I like. I've told my students this
a hundred times. If you watch the video,
the 200 ultra hard questions, I don't
know how many times. I got to tell you
guys one thing. The perfect answer isn't
always listed. You must choose from the
choices available.
Sometimes you get a question and all the
choices kind of suck.
Uh by the way, 49 and 50 are very
similar. They kind of suck. Your your
objective is just to go with the closest
to right, not the right one. You're not
looking for the absolute right. Go the
closest. Cuz if I say, "What's the color
of this wall?
Is it cream? Is it blue? Is it green or
black?" Well, you know, you got to
choose one. It's a white wall. Yeah, I
know. But you don't got that option.
Cream is the closest I got. So,
hopefully that made sense. Let's see a
question on this.
Your project team discovers a
significant security vulnerability in
the application two days before the
schedule production deployment. The
vulnerability affects user data
encryption and could potentially expose
sensitive data. What should you do?
Deploy the application as schedule and
plan to fix in the next release cycle.
Deploy the deployment. Delay the
deployment by one week to implement a
security fix that eliminate
vulnerability. Okay. Launch the v launch
the vulnerability but implement
additional measures to detect any
potential breaches quickly. Deploy to a
limited user groups to first test the
security risk and controlled before full
release.
All these answers
kind of like suck. One is delay it. The
other one is just push it out and deal
with it. I think the best answer here
though, even though it's not a good
answer, they all these answers kind of
suck.
You should never push out anything with
a security vulnerability as pushing
something out with a security
vulnerability can cause massive data
breaches
uh and can bankrupt an entire business.
So the best thing here is to don't push
it out. Even though delay in the project
is not what you want, it's probably one
of the uh better answer.
Okay,
I want to something very similar.
All right, and I just wanted to do it
again. Technically 49 and 50 is the same
thing, but I want to emphasize this. All
right.
These mindset principles are not meant
to be done in stone.
I said something earlier.
Don't fire your team members. I said
that, right?
But
you might have to follow that principle
when it's the only good option. You see,
sometimes there is no correct answer.
And sometimes going again the mindset
all the things I taught you might just
be the right answer because everything
else really sucks man
choose the best of the four it's not
about selecting it's about selecting the
best of the four I can't emphasize this
enough I want to give you more one more
example listen
what are the mindset principle is to
never defy the team member but what if
the team member is breaking the law and
is doing something against the law like
stealing company data you might have to
terminate him
okay because That's an ethics thing. Now
you're saying, "Well, that one is easy
because that was ethics." Let me give
you an example. What if you're managing
a project and you found a team member is
having arguments with other team member
and causing trouble. Now, this is an
extreme example. I'm just trying to
prove a point. What should you do?
Number one, fire the guy.
Number two, beat the hell out of him.
Physically beat him up. Number three,
have your sponsor beat this person up.
Number four, blow up the world. What do
you do? Well,
everything here is really bad and
everything really goes against the
mindset.
Well, the other the last three are
unethical, obviously, beating people up
and the first one is fire the guy. Go
with the least sucky one.
The objective on your exam guys is not
to get all the right select the right
choices. Select the best of the four. I
go over a lot with this with students
when they do my coaching program or they
we're doing questions together on
Tuesday nights.
And I and I'm like they're like Andrew B
isn't correct. And I'm like well is A C
and D correct? No.
But so B is just tiny bit better than A
C and D. B is the right answer.
The objective is to pass the test. All
right, that's your main. You go into
that exam room, pass the test, guys.
Best of the four. Let's do a practice
question on this and then we finish this
up. Your team is debating where
implement the new feature requested by a
stakeholder. The feature would enhance
user experience but require additional
development time. The sponsor supports
it, but the timeline is already tight.
Development team is split on its value.
What should you do? Implement the
feature since it enhances user
experience and have sponsor support
accepting the timeline impact as
necessary. Decline the feature to
protect the timeline original scope uh
explaining the trade-off to
stakeholders. Negotiate a compromise by
implemented a simplified version feature
that requires less development on add
the feature to the backlog to the next
project's phase acknowledging its value
while maintaining the current scope and
timeline commitments.
And this question
is where I leave off because
the answer, okay,
is
probably not the one you were going to
go with. All right, the best thing here
you can do is to try to come up with
something that you feel is best. And
this is a question that I know a lot of
you guys are going to put in the
comments. Hey, Andrew, I went with A and
I think you're wrong. Or I went with B
and I think you're wrong. I went with D
and I think you're wrong. I went with C
and you're right. I know. I know you you
guys going to you did in my 200 question
video. Probably going to do it here,
too. Here's what I'm trying to tell you
guys. I'm not going to justify this
answer. Not everything has the right
solution.
And I'm not going to go into justifying
this answer because I've gone through
all the the mindsets with you. Choose
the best answer.
Now, I'm going to go and just tell you
that the best thing I can come up with
here is negotiate. Now, I did write this
question in a way that is convoluted and
difficult, and I want people to get this
one wrong. It's very difficult when we I
was looking at this question and I was
like okay let's make it even harder
implement the feature. I don't think you
should just implement features like
that. It has a sponsor support. I think
we want to again notice they support it
but the timeline is tight. We're going
to have to push something off. I don't
think we just push it off decline it. I
don't think you should ever decline
things. I think we should work with them
to get it out. So I think DB was
definitely wrong. Add it into the next
phase. Although I like this thing. If it
brings value, maybe we could push it out
now and just adding it in. That's the
best thing I can come up with. This is
the 50 principles that you guys have. If
you want access to the PDF with all of
these questions,
and by the way, if you're watching this
in my course, if you have access to my
Udemi course, if you have access uh to
the course on the TI exams, this 35 hour
course, you already have access. I'm
going to give you this PDF if you want
it. you already have it in there here on
YouTube. You know, you could make your
uh it's hard to put documents here. All
right. So, if you want this PDF with all
these principles, check your course. You
already have it in your course. I know
most of you guys are my students
already. So, check the course
uh in there. Check the um it's going to
be attached to this video on it. All
right. Hopefully you guys enjoyed this.
This was a video a lot of people has
been asking me to make. I finally make
it. So, now you guys have it. Please
subscribe to the channel. implement
these things on your mindset. Let me
know in the description if this mindset
was helpful. Let me know if you pass
your exam with it. And guys, once again,
did you subscribe? Did you click on that
like button? Don't click it again if you
did. Guys, I wish you guys the absolute
best in passing your exam. And I'll see
you in the next video.